<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
	<title>ettedh</title>
	<link>https://ettedh.github.io/tags/human-geography/</link>
	<description>Recent content in Human Geography on ettedh</description>
	<generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
	<language>en-us</language>
	<lastBuildDate>Sun, 16 Nov 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
        <atom:link href="https://ettedh.github.io/tags/human-geography/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	
	
	<item>
		<title>River Towns</title>
		<link>https://ettedh.github.io/texts/river-towns/</link>
		<pubDate>Sun, 16 Nov 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
		
		<guid>https://ettedh.github.io/texts/river-towns/</guid>
		<description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This page is a transcription of a text by Marie E. Meyer published in 1926.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Much has been said and written about frontier life in Iowa. The grim
battles waged by the pioneer against droughts, locusts, prairie fires,
and blizzards have long been a favorite topic with the historians,
but the role of the Mississippi River has been curiously neglected.
Of course the stories of Dubuque, Davenport, Tesson, and Le Claire
are well known, but they belong more to the soil of Iowa than to its
great river.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Along the western banks of the Mississippi are little towns
that have been made and broken by the river. Many are quaint,
old-fashioned villages hugging the banks of the river and sheltered
by high bluffs from the cold winds that often sweep across the
outlying prairies. Quiet and serene, they give the impression of
being quite content with their situation, with never a dream of
expanding inland. They have an air of permanence, these old river
towns. Other settlements may be tentative communities of transient
pioneers, but the present inhabitants of the little river towns are
the grandchildren of the founders. Facing the river, they seem to
belong to it, having no desire to climb the bluffs and live on the
prairie beyond. Uneven sidewalks of flagstones, abandoned sawmills,
warehouses gauntly fronting the river and slowly sinking into decay,
the faint trace of a boat yard, an old boat landing now overgrown
with weeds and willows⁠—⁠are all mute evidences of a past that was
part of the great river. Drowsing away, living much in the past, these
towns seem to be awaiting the whistle of the long silent raft-boat
which will arouse them to activity once more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rambling, old houses of nondescript architecture line the streets that
parallel the river or cling to the steep hillsides of the diagonal
coulee. Since lumber was cheap, only the best material was used in the
mansions of a generation ago, and the rafts yielded their choicest
logs for the homes of the river men. Doors with transoms above and
kitchens finished like a steamboat cabin are eloquent reminders of
the owner&amp;rsquo;s occupation. Occasionally, the pilot house or the cabin of
an old boat was the beginning of a comfortable residence of later days.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These are not typical country towns, for the farmer and the river man
had very little in common. The farmers came to trade and sell their
produce, but they were really outsiders, onlookers at the various
activities that filled the lives of the river folk. A certain dash,
an air of sophistication, and worldly experience born of many trips
to New Orleans and Saint Louis distinguished the dwellers of these
towns from their rural neighbors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Transportation of both freight and passengers was made by boat.
As late as 1900, several towns in &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Scott_County,_Iowa&#34;&gt;Scott County&lt;/a&gt; boasted no railroad
connections with the outside world. A hack made daily trips of
fifteen or more miles from Le Claire to Davenport during the winter
months and steamboats served in the open season. The mail, carried by
rail to Illinois towns opposite, was ferried across to the Iowa shore.
And crossing the Mississippi in an open boat when the ice breaks up
in the spring is no enviable task.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The river man was a type. Just as the sea captain was devoted
to his ship, so was the river man devoted to the river and its
traditions. An aristocracy of the river was the natural product of
the golden age on the Mississippi. The names of captains, pilots, and
lumbermen were known from New Orleans to Saint Paul. Sons followed
in their father&amp;rsquo;s wake and, learning river lore from childhood, they
often served apprenticeships as cub pilots under men who had been
associates of Mark Twain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After the ice went out in the spring, every able-bodied man was ready to
go on a boat, and he stayed until the fleet laid up in October or
November (today, it may be only a government boat engaged in surveying,
dredging, or marking the river). With their season&amp;rsquo;s earnings captains,
pilots, deck hands, and stokers all settled down to a comfortable
and idle winter. Of course, it can be truthfully said that many of
these families who enjoyed beefsteak in the fall probably ate liver
in the spring. But merchants were lenient in advancing credit, so why
bother about bills? No river man of the old school found employment
elsewhere when off the river, for he knew no other trade or business.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Saloons, gambling rooms, billiard parlors, dances, and other social
activities provided entertainment and recreation during the long winter
months. Show boats, which have recently found a place in American
literature, visited these river towns regularly. Just as the circus
band drew small boys to the tent, so did the calliope draw them to the
river bank. The saloon flourished above all other places of business,
drink being the greatest weakness of the river man. A town of about
two thousand inhabitants at one time boasted of thirteen saloons!
Tying up for the night at a town was the signal for a celebration,
and probably more than one member of the crew needed assistance in
returning to the boat. No wonder the notoriously tough river towns
were the object of many revivals and prayer meetings!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The typical river man was a genial fellow, liberal with his money
which went more easily than it came. He was not much worried about the
future, for he assumed that the river would always provide a living.
So it is that few river men died rich, and many in their old age
depended solely upon the small pension granted by former employers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How the heart of the merchant in river towns was gladdened in those
old days when a steamboat whistled, and a boat was put out to shore, or
when a landing was made!  No wonder he slept above his store, for
boats came and went by night as well as by day. Once, while looking
through some papers in my father&amp;rsquo;s desk, I found an old order for
supplies to be ready when the boat passed Le Claire. It contained
thirty-six items, including canned goods, fresh fruits and vegetables,
hams, toothpicks, soap, molasses, and brooms.  A footnote attached,
stating that only goods of the best quality would be accepted, was
proof that the crews were well fed, and that the packets spread a
bounteous table for the passengers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;River cooks were noted for their skill, and many favorite dishes among
the housewives in river towns today were originally prepared on the
steamers. With a great abundance of everything, the packet cooks found
no difficulty in creating dishes that would tempt the traveler. Three
or four kinds of meat, innumerable vegetables, both hot and cold
breads, fruits, and pastries were included in each meal. Indeed,
I have very pleasant childhood memories of stolen visits to a boat
whose cook was a favorite of all children, and never did we leave
empty-handed. Amusing stories are often related about these cooks; of
he who carried salt in one vest pocket and pepper in the other pocket,
and of the one who annually cast a pan of biscuits into the water in
memory of all river cooks who were dead.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since life was centered about the river, it is only natural that the
arrival and departure of a boat was more or less of an event to the
children. Many youngsters learned to read by spelling out the names of
favorite boats, and such fascinating names they were⁠—⁠&lt;i&gt;Phil
Sheridan&lt;/i&gt;, &lt;i&gt;Red Wing&lt;/i&gt;, &lt;i&gt;Northwestern&lt;/i&gt;, &lt;i&gt;LeClaire
Belle&lt;/i&gt;,&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:2&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; &lt;i&gt;Eclipse&lt;/i&gt;, &lt;i&gt;Diamond Jo&lt;/i&gt;, &lt;i&gt;North Star&lt;/i&gt;,
&lt;i&gt;Saturn&lt;/i&gt;⁠—⁠all symbolical of romance and adventure. Mothers
constantly worried about their children playing on log rafts, or
riding the waves in small skiffs, and scarcely a season passed when
some child was not pulled out of the water more dead than alive. It
was perfectly natural that the river children took to the water like
ducks. Truant boys could usually be located along the river bank or on
small islands playing Robinson Crusoe in a shack of logs and willows.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just as the cowboy had words and phrases peculiar to his life and
occupation, so the river man&amp;rsquo;s vocabulary abounded in provincialisms
and characteristic terms. No little girl ever dreamed of calling a rope
other than a line, and all unskilled work on a boat was referred to as
&lt;i&gt;decking&lt;/i&gt;. The cook&amp;rsquo;s helpers were called &amp;ldquo;slush-cooks&amp;rdquo;; &lt;i&gt;roosters&lt;/i&gt;
were the men employed on raft-boats, possibly so called because they
slept anywhere, always ready to go out on the raft. To address an old
river man by the title of &lt;i&gt;captain&lt;/i&gt; was the height of flattery.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, the river man was a teller of tales⁠—⁠many true, some the
delightfully improbable yarns spun on the deck, in the engine room,
or around a card table. Politics had no fascination for these men,
and rarely did a discussion of that kind disturb the minds or excite
the temper of the genial group. Stories of races between rival boats
(that most famous of all races between the &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Robert_E._Lee_%28steamboat%29&#34;&gt;&lt;i&gt;Natchez&lt;/i&gt; and the
&lt;i&gt;Robert E. Lee&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt; still excites comment), storms on Lake Pepin,
tie-ups in Cattail Slough, broken rafts, black nights when the rain fell
in sheets and only instinct guided the pilot&amp;rsquo;s hand, of the mate who
ruled his crew by carrying the spoke of a wagon wheel about with
him⁠—⁠all these and many more offer a rich field of romance and adventure
for the professional story-teller.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tragedy stalked along the Iowa shores in Civil War times when cholera
raged along the river. When the &lt;i&gt;Canada&lt;/i&gt;, a North Line packet
operating between Saint Louis and Saint Paul, cleared Saint Louis, she
was free from the dread disease. But case after case broke out, and
just below Le Claire a landing was made, and the victims were quickly
buried on a nearby bluff. The graves were marked by rude stones from
which the lettering has long since been obliterated by wind and sand.
And again from the lower Mississippi during the Civil War comes the
story of the &lt;i&gt;Sultana&lt;/i&gt; which was blown up near Memphis, Tennessee,
and fourteen hundred Union soldiers lost their lives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We children were much interested in one white-haired pilot who for
years brought a packet up from Saint Louis. He had given his dog
to some friends, and every time the packet whistled, &amp;ldquo;Maje&amp;rdquo; dashed to
the boat landing, eagerly and affectionately greeting his old master.
In his younger days, Maje had been trained to look through the boats
and barges for stowaways and seeping water. No watchman was needed
to bring out the former, and Maje&amp;rsquo;s wet feet were proof of the latter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since the steamboats all had distinguishing whistles, no one needed to
scan the river to learn what boat was coming in. Only a few weeks ago,
I heard one of the few remaining steamers whistling a greeting to the
captain&amp;rsquo;s wife as the boat went up the river.  But the long rafts,
carefully guarded by the towboat and the bow-boat which used
to float slowly past our house, have disappeared forever. Gone also
are the packets white and trim, and the side-wheelers churning the
water impatiently, with the captain on his bridge giving orders to
the sweating, hurrying crew, while presiding over all the bustle and
apparent confusion stood the pilot, serenely aloof and remote behind
his wheel, confident of his knowledge of an ever-changing river.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Possibly not many people know that the Mississippi contains a series
of rapids between the city of Davenport and the town of Le Claire.
A government canal and locks have done away with the necessity of
running the rapids, but before this canal was constructed, every boat
was steered over the rapids by a special pilot. Raft boats never
ventured over these rapids at night, and when the water was low, the
raft was divided and taken over in sections.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whoever has lived in an old river town who can not recall the ghostly
play of the lights along the shore as the pilot sought a landing;
the creak of the lowering gangplank; the shouts of the mate and the
crew as they made fast the lines? But the old river life is gone.
The last raft floated around the bend of the river fifteen years
ago, and many of the old river aristocracy and lesser members have
passed on. Only the quiet little river towns remain, sole relics of
the romantic time when the Mississippi was the principal highway to
Iowa, when steamboating was an art as well as a job, and when culture
and gaiety reigned in the ports on the Father of Waters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnotes&#34;&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:1&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Marie E. Meyer, &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;https://hdl.handle.net/2027/mdp.39015039514545&amp;amp;seq=461&#34;&gt;River Towns&lt;/a&gt;,&amp;rdquo; &lt;em&gt;The Palimpsest&lt;/em&gt;, vol. 7:12 (1926).&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:2&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/LeClaire,_Iowa&#34;&gt;Le Claire, Iowa&lt;/a&gt;. Officially spelled &lt;i&gt;LeClaire&lt;/i&gt;.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
	</item>
	
	<item>
		<title>Chicago Amtrak Directions</title>
		<link>https://ettedh.github.io/articles/amtrak-ns/</link>
		<pubDate>Thu, 09 Oct 2025 17:43:47 -0500</pubDate>
		
		<guid>https://ettedh.github.io/articles/amtrak-ns/</guid>
		<description>&lt;p&gt;Chicago&amp;rsquo;s Union Station is the most connected rail station in the United States. It is a double stub-end terminal, meaining that trains can come from either the north or the south.&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; As it turns out, all Amtrak lines, except for the &lt;em&gt;Empire Builder&lt;/em&gt; and its subsets, come to the south end.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;https://ettedh.github.io/pics/amtrak-ns.svg&#34; alt=&#34;A map of the United States, showing places accessible to the north in red, and to the south in blue&#34;&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;States accessible to the north (red) and south (blue) from Chicago Union Station. Illinois has stations to both directions.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most of this is due to Lake Michigan. Any direction to the east has to go around the south shore, including Michigan to the northeast. Thus, the north side has only &lt;em&gt;two&lt;/em&gt; cardinal directions (north and northwest), whereas the south has the other six: everywhere from California to Massachusetts.&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:2&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most states are accessible from Chicago. Two (South Dakota and Wyoming) have no stations whatsoever. Alabama and the New England states have only regional access. And the other two are obviously not reachable by rail.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnotes&#34;&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:1&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are a couple of under-utilized through-running platforms. &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.hsrail.org/blog/its-time-to-fix-union-station/#through&#34;&gt;Many rail users&lt;/a&gt; think that more through-running is a necessary improvement.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:2&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can find the detailed alignments from Andrew Lynch&amp;rsquo;s beatiful &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.vanshnookenraggen.com/_index/2020/12/complete-and-geographically-accurate-track-map-of-chicago/&#34;&gt;Chicago Track Map&lt;/a&gt;,&amp;rdquo; last modified in 2025.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
	</item>
	
	<item>
		<title>Early Alaska Transportation</title>
		<link>https://ettedh.github.io/texts/alaska/</link>
		<pubDate>Sat, 04 Oct 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
		
		<guid>https://ettedh.github.io/texts/alaska/</guid>
		<description>&lt;p&gt;The period of evolution from man-carried burdens to
railroad transport, from raft and dugout to steamboat,
is coextensive with the advance of man from savagery to
civilization, a period to be measured by many thousands of
years. In Alaska, however, the most primitive modes of
transport are often found side by side with the most highly
developed: the prospector leaving a railroad coach and
shouldering his heavy pack becomes a beast of burden, as
was the man of the stone age; the tourist may photograph
from comfortable steamers the little bark canoe of the
Yukon native; a modern ocean steamer anchored at Nome
will be visited by the primitive skin boats of the Eskimo.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Less than two decades ago, no Alaskan valleys had echoed
in the whistle of the locomotive, and a score of its navigable
rivers had never felt the rhythmic chug of the
steamer. Now&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; there are over seven hundred miles of railroad in the
Territory, and some form of steamboat service is found
on nearly all Alaskan rivers. Of the tens of thousands
who essayed the heart-breaking task of dragging and carrying
their supplies through the passages in the mountainous
coastal barrier, there were probably few who could realize
that within a few years it would be possible to reach the
Yukon by rail in not-as-many days as they took months
for the journey.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;https://ettedh.github.io/pics/alaska/dog-rails.webp&#34; alt=&#34;A team of three dogs carrying two men on a handcar&#34;/&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt; Dog team pulling a
wheeled vehicle over the railroads tracks on the Seward Penisula, photo by J. B. Mertie.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Transport is the very essence of frontier life. Progress
of industry and settlement are absolutely controlled by the
means of transport. The pioneer whose mission is to obtain
or to harvest rich deposits of &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Placer_mining&#34;&gt;placer gold&lt;/a&gt; can, by hard
labor, carry out his projects through means of transport
of his own development. If, however, other resources are
to be utilized, such as the fertility of the soil, beds of coal,
deposits of copper and gold veins, and if permanent settlements
are to be made and homes to be built, steamboats,
railroads, and wagon roads must be provided.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While much the larger part of Alaska is still almost as
inaccessible as it was in its earliest history, yet the railroads,
the automobile roads already built, and the well-established
steamer service have revolutionized the transport
system. This fact, and this alone, has made possible
the beginnings of a systematic industrial development of
the Northland. The relative efficiency and approximate
cost of the most important means of transport in Alaska
are shown in the following table:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relative Efficiency of Alaskan Means of Transport&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
      &lt;tr&gt;
          &lt;th&gt;Type&lt;/th&gt;
          &lt;th style=&#34;text-align: center&#34;&gt;Weight carried&lt;/th&gt;
          &lt;th style=&#34;text-align: center&#34;&gt;Miles traveled in 24 hours&lt;/th&gt;
          &lt;th style=&#34;text-align: center&#34;&gt;Approx. cost per ton mile&lt;/th&gt;
          &lt;th style=&#34;text-align: center&#34;&gt;Notes&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
      &lt;tr&gt;
          &lt;td&gt;Backpacking&lt;/td&gt;
          &lt;td style=&#34;text-align: center&#34;&gt;50 lbs. per man&lt;/td&gt;
          &lt;td style=&#34;text-align: center&#34;&gt;12&lt;/td&gt;
          &lt;td style=&#34;text-align: center&#34;&gt;$25.00&lt;/td&gt;
          &lt;td style=&#34;text-align: center&#34;&gt;Wages $7.50 per day.&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;/tr&gt;
      &lt;tr&gt;
          &lt;td&gt;Pack horse&lt;/td&gt;
          &lt;td style=&#34;text-align: center&#34;&gt;200 lbs. per horse&lt;/td&gt;
          &lt;td style=&#34;text-align: center&#34;&gt;12&lt;/td&gt;
          &lt;td style=&#34;text-align: center&#34;&gt;$12.00&lt;/td&gt;
          &lt;td style=&#34;text-align: center&#34;&gt;Based on actual charges.&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;/tr&gt;
      &lt;tr&gt;
          &lt;td&gt;Dog sled&lt;/td&gt;
          &lt;td style=&#34;text-align: center&#34;&gt;100 lbs. per dog&lt;/td&gt;
          &lt;td style=&#34;text-align: center&#34;&gt;15&lt;/td&gt;
          &lt;td style=&#34;text-align: center&#34;&gt;$2.50&lt;/td&gt;
          &lt;td style=&#34;text-align: center&#34;&gt;Based on actual charges.&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;/tr&gt;
      &lt;tr&gt;
          &lt;td&gt;Wagon road&lt;/td&gt;
          &lt;td style=&#34;text-align: center&#34;&gt;500 lbs. per horse&lt;/td&gt;
          &lt;td style=&#34;text-align: center&#34;&gt;20&lt;/td&gt;
          &lt;td style=&#34;text-align: center&#34;&gt;$0.60&lt;/td&gt;
          &lt;td style=&#34;text-align: center&#34;&gt;Two-horse team at $20 per day.&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;/tr&gt;
      &lt;tr&gt;
          &lt;td&gt;Railroad&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:2&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
          &lt;td style=&#34;text-align: center&#34;&gt;700 tons per train&lt;/td&gt;
          &lt;td style=&#34;text-align: center&#34;&gt;300&lt;/td&gt;
          &lt;td style=&#34;text-align: center&#34;&gt;$0.08&lt;/td&gt;
          &lt;td style=&#34;text-align: center&#34;&gt;Frontier railroad.&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;/tr&gt;
      &lt;tr&gt;
          &lt;td&gt;Canoe or poling boat&lt;/td&gt;
          &lt;td style=&#34;text-align: center&#34;&gt;1000 lbs. per boat&lt;/td&gt;
          &lt;td style=&#34;text-align: center&#34;&gt;20&lt;/td&gt;
          &lt;td style=&#34;text-align: center&#34;&gt;$1.50&lt;/td&gt;
          &lt;td style=&#34;text-align: center&#34;&gt;Two men, wages at $7.50 per day.&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;/tr&gt;
      &lt;tr&gt;
          &lt;td&gt;River steamers&lt;/td&gt;
          &lt;td style=&#34;text-align: center&#34;&gt;500 tons&lt;/td&gt;
          &lt;td style=&#34;text-align: center&#34;&gt;250&lt;/td&gt;
          &lt;td style=&#34;text-align: center&#34;&gt;$0.05&lt;/td&gt;
          &lt;td style=&#34;text-align: center&#34;&gt;Average of river steamer freight.&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Though the cost figures given in this table are only an
approximation, yet they give a measure of the difficulties
with which the pioneer who provides his own transport
has to contend and show why large industrial advancement
is only possible when modern means of transport are available.
Historical evidence of this truth is also found in the
evolution of Alaskan settlement and industry. Until the
Klondike gold was discovered in the 1890s, the only settlements
in Alaska of any importance were at tidewater.
The great interior contained only a few roving prospectors,
and a dozen trading posts on the Yukon and Kuskokwim
rivers were the only permanent settlements. The extraordinarily
rich gold deposits of the Klondike and later those
of Fairbanks, Nome, and other camps, made possible certain
industrial advancements, but these constituted no permanent
prosperity. It is only the construction of railroads
and wagon roads which has led to the development of the
resources of inland regions other than the rich placers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;commercial-shipping&#34;&gt;Commercial shipping&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When we took over Alaska from Russia, commerce, as
has been previously pointed out, was confined to that of
the fur trader along the coast and the lower courses of
the Yukon and Kuskokwim rivers. The coastal settlements
were served by a few smaller steamers, and extraneous
commerce was by sailing vessels chiefly operating between
Sitka and Petropavlovsk on the east shore of Kamchatka.
Once a year, a ship arrived direct from Kronstadt on the
Baltic. The few overland journeys of the Russians were
by dog teams, and traffic on the rivers was by skin boats
or scows.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The steamers carrying the Commission and the troops
to Alaska in 1867 were among the first ocean steamers to
be seen in these waters.&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:3&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; At this time, the steamer &lt;i&gt;John L.
Stephens&lt;/i&gt; also made her first voyage from San Francisco
to Sitka. This inaugurated a monthly service which was
the only communication with Alaska for twenty years, when a
semi-monthly service was begun.&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:4&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:4&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; These vessels ran from
San Francisco to Sitka and Wrangell, with occasional stops
at other settlements in Southeastern Alaska. After 1871,
when the Cassiar gold discovery of British Columbia was
made, a field which was reached by the Stikine River route,
the Wrangell call be came the most important, for this
city was then the industrial center of Alaska. It could
also be reached by a small vessel operated by the Hudson
Bay Company which gave an intermittent service between
Victoria and Wrangell.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For over twenty years, the traveler who wished to go beyond
Sitka had to rely on the occasional vessels of the Revenue
Cutter Service or the fur companies, or on the small craft
of the fisherman and the small trader, for there was no
regular communication with other Alaskan ports. There
was no mail service outside of Southeastern Alaska until
1891, when a contract was made to carry mail to Unalaska
during the summer months.&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:5&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:5&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; It fell to Alaska Commercial
Company, which took over the fur trade of the
Russian American Company and obtained the first lease on
the Seal Islands, to establish communication with Alaskan
ports other than those of Southeastern Alaska. The company
posts on Cook Inlet, Kodiak, Unalaska, and Saint Michael
were reached by vessels running to San Francisco. At
first, small steam schooners were used, later vessels of
a thousand tons or more, Early in the ’70s, a more or less regular
communication was established with the principal ports,
later developing into a regular carrier servidce. By 1879,
the steamer &lt;i&gt;St. Paul&lt;/i&gt; was making a seasonal call at Saint
Michael, ant the famous little steamer &lt;i&gt;Dora&lt;/i&gt; was supplying
the ports on the Aleutian and Pribilof islands. Later,
the steamers running to Kodiak and Saint Michael became
public carriers, and the same was true of the river steamers
on the Yukon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src=&#34;https://ettedh.github.io/pics/alaska/dora.webp&#34; alt=&#34;A two-mast ship sailing in front of an Alaskan fjord&#34;/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;The “Dora,” photo by D. F. Higgins&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;i&gt;Dora&lt;/i&gt; is perhaps the most famous of Alaska’s vessels,
and has a record of forty years of service. At different times,
she has served as a poacher of seal on the high seas, as a
transport for furs and supplies, as a passenger boat, and
finally as a fish boat. Originally built as a brig, she was
later given steam power and for years plowed the dangerous
waters of the Bering Sea. From 1891 to 1900, the &lt;i&gt;Dora&lt;/i&gt;
plied between Sitka and the ports to the westward as far
as Unalaska. In 1900, she carried the local traffic from
Saint Michael to Nome and other settlements along the southern
coast of the Bering Sea. Later, for many years, she was
the mail boat between Seward and Alaska Peninsula ports.
The &lt;i&gt;Dora&lt;/i&gt;, in spite of her great age, was always a staunch
sea craft and weathered many a fierce gale that carried her
hither and yon, for she had little steam power. She has
perhaps the record for carrying more passengers with more
discomfort than any vessel which ever reached Alaskan
waters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Though the reaching of Alaskan ports in the early history
of the Territory presented many vexations, delays,
and difficulties, these were the least of the transportation
obstacles met with by the pioneer. Once landed with his
outfit, he had to make further progress entirely on his own
efforts. It was then a question of packing his supplies
on his back, building his own boat—or, where conditions
favored, making use of dog teams.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;sleds&#34;&gt;Sleds&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Countless generations of Alaskan natives have used the
dog for transport, and he is to Alaska what the yak is to
India, or the llama to Peru. The climatic and topographic
features of the Pacific seaboard are not favorable to sledding:
the winter snows do not last long enough; and the
heavy timbers and steep slopes also make the use of dog
teams impractical. But the gently rolling upland region
of the interior with its broad flat valleys and lack of thick
timber furnished admirable sleigh routes, especially over
the smooth surfaces of the many watercourses. The long
cold winters also favored sled transportation, the season
extending from November to May. The snowfall seldom
exceeds three feet, but it remains continuous all winter,
a fact which also favored the use of sleds.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hand sleds have been used as well as dog sleds, and many
a gold seeker dragged his heavy sled for hundreds of miles.
From 150 to 200 pounds is all a man can pull over an
average trail. But in sledding over river or lake ice, he
can take advantage of fair winds by employing improvised
sails of the type used on the upper Yukon during the
Klondike rush. The dog sled is, however, the typical
mode of transport in inland Alaska as well as for the tundra
region of the Bering Sea and Arctic Ocean. Originally
there were two rather sharply differentiated types of sled
dogs in Alaska: the malamute or &lt;i&gt;Eskimo dog&lt;/i&gt;, and the
“husky” or dog introduced from the Mackenzie valley,
probably by the Hudson Bay traders.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;dogs&#34;&gt;Dogs&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The malamute, originally the sled dog of the Bering Sea
and Arctic coastal region, is now widely distributed in
the Interior. The same family of dogs is found along the
entire Arctic coast of Canada and in Greenland, and has
provided the power for most of the sleds of the Arctic
explorers. Their short, stocky build, their strong shoulders,
their pointed ears and noses, and their gracefully arched
tails are familiar to all through the illustrations in narratives
of polar adventure. A good-sized malamute will weigh
75 or 80 pounds. The malamute varies in color from almost
snow white to black, gray, and mottled.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The husky has longer legs and body than the malamute,
is loosely built, and has a dense though shorter coat of
fur. His resemblance to a timber wolf is very strong, and
he appears to be a much more powerful animal than the
malamute. He is more vicious too, but he is nevertheless
perhaps the favorite sled dog, especially in the heavy
freighting of the interior.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Yukon Indians also had a dog on the first coming of
the white man. It resembled the malamute but was smaller
and not so powerful. These dogs, generally called &lt;i xml:lang=&#34;chn&#34;&gt;siwash&lt;/i&gt;,
are probably the degenerate offspring of the coastal malamute;
and generations of underfeeding and abuse have
produced an inferior breed. It is probable that the Athabaskans,
the true Indians of the interior, got their first
knowledge of sled dogs from the Eskimo.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The pure breeds of both malamute and husky are rapidly
disappearing along the well-traveled routes by the inbreeding
of native with imported stock. Many drivers
prefer these cross-breed dogs, the offspring of native dogs
and collies, setters, pointers, spaniels, Newfoundlands, and
Saint Bernards. The pure-bred imported dogs, while more
intelligent and tractable than the native animals, have not
their endurance and resistance. One of the great faults
is the tenderness of their feet on a rough trail. Some of
the half-breeds, however, combine the endurance of their
native blood with the intelligence and gentleness of their
imported ancestors, and these make the most valuable
draft animals. A common practice is to use an outside
dog as the intelligent leader of a team of more hardy
native dogs. The leader controlled by the commands of
the driver, guides the dogs that follow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dried salmon is the standard dog food throughout Alaska.
It is surprising how much work a dog can perform on a
pound and a half of salmon a day. Large dogs engaged in
continuous travel should, however, receive from two and
a half to three pounds of food a day. They show the greatest
endurance when fed a diet of fish and a cereal, such as
rice or oatmeal, and bacon or lard at a ratio of 1:1½;
and the best practice is to cook all the food,
which, of course, is necessary for the cereal. Dogs are
fed only at night, no morning or noon meal being provided.
Most of the Indian dogs, and indeed many of those owned
by whites, in summer are much undernourished. This
makes them most arrant thieves, and every cache of provisions
must by carefully barricaded against dogs. Even
well-fed sled dogs are not to be trusted and will devour
or destroy footwear and even their own harness. The native
dogs require no housing in the coldest winter weather and,
after being fed, will curl up and sleep in the snow, even
though a blizzard be howling. Their shaggy skins are
proof against the mosquito, ever present in the summer, but
these insects sometimes torture them by stings about the
eyes and nose.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;https://ettedh.github.io/pics/alaska/backpacker.webp&#34; alt=&#34;Man with a backpack flanked by four pack dogs on a rutted trail&#34;/&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Backpacking man and dogs (photographer unknown)&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is no standard size for an Alaskan dog team. A
prospector may drag a sled loaded with his 200 or 300
pounds of supplies with the aid of a single dog, or a driver
may have a team of nine dogs or more. A driving team,
however, usually includes not less than five or not more
than nine dogs. Much larger teams are sometimes used
for heavy freight. There is a known instnace of dogs being
used for hauling the heavy steel shaft of a gold dredge
from Knik, at the head of Cook Inlet, to the Idiatarod
district, a distance of nearly five hundred miles; the route led over
a mountain pass in the heart of the Alaska Range and,
though the journey was performed under great difficulties,
the trip was completed successfully.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sled dogs are hitched both tandem and in pairs, with
an extra leader. For tandem driving, traces are used, and
the rig is not unlike that for horses. In pair driving, the
traces of each dog are merely hitched to a single tow line.
If the dogs are staggered along the tow line, the team
can adjust itself to any width of trail. The fan-shaped rig
of Greenland, by which each dog is attached to the sled
by a separate tow line and the team spreads out radially,
is not adapted to narrow trails and is unknown in Alaska.
Each dog is fitted with a padded leather collar from which
his traces reach back and are attached to the tow line.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Distance of a day’s trail for a dog team and weight pulled
vary so much, depending on condition of trail, on graident
of course, and on weight and endurance of dogs, that it is
dififcult to generalize. Where a new trail is being broken
and where there are steep gradients, 50 pounds to the dog
is an ample load. Indeed, in some cross-country journeys,
this load may have to be reduced to 30 or 40 pounds. On
the other hand, over a smooth, hard, level trail, strong
dogs have been known to drag as much as 300 pounds. It
is probably safe to say that a good dog on hard, level trails
should haul 100 pounds—that is, about 25 percent more
than his own weight. this load he will not take over 15
or 20 miles a day. Reduce this weight to 50 pounds, and
the dog should make 25 miles a day. The famous dog races
at Nome have shown that a dog team hauling only the
empty sled can average nearly 90 miles a day for five
days.&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:6&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:6&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; The winter mail contracts call, on the average, for
a speed of 22 miles a day; but the carriers frequently
exceed this, runs of over 40 miles a day having been recorded.
The mail carriers haul from 50 to 75 pounds of
weight per dog.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;https://ettedh.github.io/pics/alaska/dog-team.webp&#34; /&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;b&gt;The Alaskan dog team.&lt;/b&gt; Dogs are used for hauling sleds over the snow on cross country trips, photo by J.&amp;nbsp;B. Mertie.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many long journeys have been made over well-beaten
trails by good “dog mushers” where a day’s average travel
was 25 miles. This, however, is hard work for the driver
as well as the dogs. The driver seldom rides on the sled,
except on down grades, but runs behind, guiding and
steadying it by the handle bars. Where a new trail has
to be broken through new snow, a man on snowshoes goes
in advance of the team.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The dog sleds are 8⁠–⁠12 feet long and about 20⁠–⁠24
inches wide. They are strong, built of hickory or oak,
and made not too rigid. A certain looseness and pliability
allow the runners to follow the tracks. Small sleds weigh
about 75 pounds, large ones nearly 200. For freighting,
flat sleds are used, sometimes with a “gee pole” for guiding
at the front where the driver helps haul the load, sometimes
with the gee pole at the rear. Travel sleds are made
with a basked superstructure and two handles at the rear.
These are used by the driver to guide the sled, and when
opportunity offers he steps on the rear of the sled for
short rides.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dogs are also used in summer to a limited extent as
pack animals by both Eskimo and Indian, and occasionally
a lone prospector will be found to make a similar use of
them. A dog will pack 20 or 30, even 40 pounds. Unless
thoroughly broken, these dogs are difficult to control, and
one of their favorite tricks is to lie down in water, pack
and all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;https://ettedh.github.io/pics/alaska/portage.webp&#34; alt=&#34;Four men carrying a canoe through a wetland&#34; /&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Men on portage from one stream to another. Photo by J. B. Mertie&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Backpacking is the most primitive and laborious mode
of transport and is resorted to only when all other means
fail. As an actual means of forwarding supplies, it is
used only between navigable waters, namely on portages.
A portage is chosen, so far as circumstances permit, so
as to afford firm footing and easy grades. The Chilkoot
Pass is the most famous portage in the world, for thousands
of tons of supplies have been carried across it. It lies
some twenty miles from, and 3,100 feet above, tidewater; and,
as has been indicated earlier, the approach to it, though
easy enough at first, beocmes steep and difficult. To the
place called &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nps.gov/klgo/learn/historyculture/the-scales-history.htm&#34;&gt;the Scales&lt;/a&gt;, sledding was feasible; but from
here on, a steep climb to the summit has to be made, and
transport was on the backs of men. This portage provided
the test that winnowed out the strong from the weak, the
stout-hearted from the failures. The average man found,
at least at the start, that 50 pounds was a heavy load up
the steep ascent; many learned later to carry 100 pounds,
though such a burden was a serious strain on the heart, and
some whose determination was greater than their strength
succumbed under it. Over an ordinary portage with hard
trail and no grade, most physically strong men will carry
100 pounds; and experienced packers will take 150 or even
200 pounds on a cross-country trip, through the hills and
mountains. But relatively few will carry more than 50
pounds, and that amount not over fifteen miles a day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;horses&#34;&gt;Horses&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the Pacific seaboard region of Alaska, the best grasslands
are along the shores of Cook Inlet, on the Alaska
Peninsula, and on Kodiak Island. But these areas are by
no means all the grazing lands, and grass is sufficiently
abundant elsewhere to make the use of horses feasible
for summer journeys. There is much good pasturage in
the Susitna valley, especially on its western margin in the
Yentna River basin. The Copper River has less grazing
land in its basin, but it suffices for the traveler. Summer
pastures sufficient for pack train are widely distributed
in the great inland region beyond the Pacific ranges and
northward as far as the Arctic Mountains which divide
the Yukon waters from those flowing northward into the
Arctic Ocean. Some splendid grasslands are found in this
region, for example along the Tanana and its tributaries.
In other places again, such as north of the Yukon, the
grass is scant, but patches sufficient for a pack train can
usually be found at distances not exceeding a day’s march.
Horses have been used by the Geological Survey as far
north as the Arctic divide, and the International Boundary
Commission took a pack train all the way to the Arctic
Ocean along the 141st meridian, north of the Porcupine
River. As the Bering Sea is approached, nutritious grass becomes
scanter and is confined chiefly to the highlands, the
extensive lowlands being chiefly covered with moss and
marsh grass. In this region, only careful planning and
search for pasture will permit the use of pack horses.
Much the same is true of Seward Peninsula, though the
Geological Survey expeditions have traversed its entire
area with pack trains. There is some grassland even in
the Arctic Slope region of Alaska, but not in sufficient
abundance to make long pack train trips feasible. It is
probably safe to estimate that there are in Alaska some
300,000 square miles in which the grass is sufficiently abundant to permit the use of a pack train.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Horses were brought to the Yukon as early as 1885, but
they were relatively little used until the Klondike rush.
The first long pack train trip in Alaska was that made in
1891 by E. J. Glave and Jack Dalton when they went from
the coast into the Lake Kluane region, previously discussed
in Chapter 16.&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:7&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:7&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; The Army exploration of 1898
were made in part with pack horses, and in 1899 the
Geological Survey first used horses. That summer, W. J.
Peters and I made the journey from Haines in Southeastern
Alaska to Eagle on the Yukon, a distance of nearly six hundred
miles, that has already been referred to in Chapter 16.
In 1902, I made what is perhaps the longest pack horse
journey ever accomplished in Alaska: from Cook Inlet, round the base of Mount McKinley, and on to the Yukon at
Rampart. In 105 days, the pack train traveled some 800
miles with the personnel going entirely on foot. At the
start, the horses were each loaded with 250 pound sacks;
but, as provisions were consumed at the rate of about 21
pounds a day, the packs gradually became lighter. On the
other hand, some of the least strong of the horses were so
weakened by the arduous trail and by the insect pest that
they had to be shot before the journey was half over; at
the end of the trip only nine of the original 20 animals
remained.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During such journeys the animals find their food in the
native grasses which are very nourishing. There is in
Alaska, however, no natural curing of grasses such as
takes place in the arid states of the West. When frost comes, about the middle of September, the horse feed is
practically ruined. Therefore, the use of pack horses in
Alaska is pretty much limited to the season from June 1
to the middle of September. By feeding grain one can
considerably extend the season, but as a horse will eat up
his own load in ten or fifteen days, such use is impractical for
long journeys.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;https://ettedh.github.io/pics/alaska/horses-swimming.webp&#34; alt=&#34;Two horses up to their heads in water. Next to them are three men paddling a canoe.&#34;/&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Pack train of horses swimming a stream. Photo by A. H. Brooks&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Horse sleds, like pack animals, only came into general
use after the Klondike discovery. Their efficient use is
limited to roads which must be at least passable after the
winter snow comes. In the early days there was much
horse sledding over the ice of the Yukon and other rivers.
But even this implies the breaking of a trail, and the use of
horse sleds is now limited to established winter roads.
Before good sled roads were available, many so-called
“double enders” were in use. These are small sleds, not
unlike the freight sleds pulled by dogs, that are drawn by
a single horse or by two driven tandem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before trails passable for sleds were established, a mode
of transport called &lt;i&gt;raw hiding&lt;/i&gt; was sometimes resorted
to. In this, freight was securely lashed into bales which were encased in raw hides, to which the traces of horses
were attached. Such bales could be dragged over any trail,
and even over bare ground, on which the horse could find
footing, for it was of no importance which side of the
load was on top. It was, of course, on account of the
friction, a very inefficient use of horse power and little, if
any, improvement over the back load. Now, where roads
have been built or other good sledding conditions are
found, winter horse freighting is by the familiar double-
or bobsled, known in all the northern states.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;reindeer&#34;&gt;Reindeer&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During the early years of the introduction of reindeer
into Alaska much was said about their use for transport.
It was pointed out that the advantages of the reindeer
over the dog were that he found his own food, and could
be used as pack animal in the summer and sled puller in
the winter. The enormous use of reindeer transport in
Siberia appeared fully to justify these contentions; yet
after thirty years of reindeer breeding in Alaska, their use in
transport is almost negligible. In Siberia, a sled load of
270⁠–⁠300 pounds is easily hauled for long distances by
the reindeer. But these are the large &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tungusic_peoples&#34;&gt;Tungus&lt;/a&gt; animals
which average at least a third larger than the Alaskan
reindeer, are used as saddle animals, and will carry a
rider even through deep, soft snow; as pack animals they
will carry from 100 to 200 pounds. It is difficult to understand
why a similar use in Alaska has met with such
indifferent success. In the earlier days of the reindeer
experiments Laplanders were chiefly used for training both
the reindeer themselves and the Eskimos in their use. This
was undoubtedly, as can now be seen, a mistake. The
Laplander had both the ignorance and the lack of adaptability
to a new environment inherent to his semi-civilized
state. He was dealing with a Siberian animal much wilder
than the more highly domesticated one of his own land.
The small &lt;i&gt;pulka&lt;/i&gt;, or Lapland sled, fashioned out of half
a log and rounded at the bottom, while making a good
passenger vehicle, was not adapted to hauling freight;
and the freight sled with runners was new to him. Moreover,
in Lapland, the reindeer was chiefly used to carry
men and light loads, and there was no use of the animal to transport heavy freight for long distances, such as had
been done in Siberia for many generations. As a means
of domesticating the Alaskan reindeer and of training
the natives in their use, the Laplander was almost a
complete failure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reindeer transport had, however, a more thorough test
by some of the mail contractors. These men with a keen
idea to business fully realized that if the reindeer could
be substituted for dogs there would be a material profit
in the change. The reindeer subsists on food of his own
finding, and it costs $75 to $100 a year to feed a dog. After
a period of careful test by men who had the initiative
of the frontiersman, the experiment of substituting reindeer
for dogs as mail carriers was on all but a very few
routes entirely abandoned.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are some evident reasons why the reindeer could
not be substituted for the dog. Most of the established
dog team routes are along the large waterways, and in
the great inland regions of Alaska the lichen or reindeer
moss grows only on the highlands above the timber line. Obviously
the sled reindeer could not be driven to the highlands
to obtain its pasture. Local climatic conditions were
also an obstacle. A thaw followed by a freeze might cover
the pastures with ice and make the lichens unavailable
to the reindeer. In contrast to this, the general use of dog
teams made the furnishing of dried salmon for dog feed
a well-established industry along the waterocurses. The
reindeer will eat little except its regular food of lichens,
but the dog is omnivorous in its appetite. It should be
added, however, that the great tundra areas of the Bering
Sea and of northern Alaska are the natural home of the
reindeer. The barren ground region has as yet but little
population save for the native whose mode of life has long
been adapted to the use of dogs. Hence the substitutuion of
the reindeer can only be brought about very gradually;
the change of a people from a nomadic to a pastoral life
must be a work of generation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The following description by Jarvis illustrates the use of reindeer as sled animals:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All hands must be ready at the same time when starting a deer
train, for, just as soon as the animals of the head team start,
they are all off with a jump, and for a short time keep up a very high
rate of speed. If one is not quick in jumping and holding on to his
sled, he is likely either to lose his team or be dragged along in the
snow. They soon come down to a moderate gait, however, and finally
drop into a walk when tired. They are harnessed with a well-fitting
collar of two flat pieces of wood, from which a trace goes back on
each side to the ends of a breast or single tree that fits under the
body. From the center of this a single trace runs back to the sled
either between or to ine side of the hind legs. In the wake of the
legs this trace is protected with soft fur, or the skin will soon be
worn through with the constant chafing. Generally, there is a single
line made fast to the left side of a halter and with this the animal
is to be guided and held in check; but this line must be kept slack
and on only when the deer is to be guided or stopped. By pulling
hard on this line, the weight of the sled comes on the head and
the animal is soon brought to a standstill, though often this is only
accomplished after he has gone in a circle several times and you
and the sleds are in a general mix-up. No whip is used and none
should be, for the deer are very timid and easily frightened and ince
gotten in that state are hard to quiet and control. A little tugging
on the lines will generally start them off even when they balk. The
sleds in use are very low and wide with very broad runners.&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:8&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:8&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During the past decade much advance has been made
in the training of sled deer by the Eskimo, mainly because
of the supervision and encouragement of W. T. Lopp and
his assistants of the Alaska Reindeer Service. The use of
sled deer is gradually becoming a part of the industrial
life of the Eskimo, and the more intelligent herders are
shoring an increasing facility in handling them. The
superintendents of the Alaska Native School and the Reindeer
Service are making much use of reindeer in their
winter journeys of inspection. The journeys of one winter
using reindeer aggregated 1,300 miles, and the average
normal day’s travel was 28 miles. It is also worthy of note
that native reindeer races have established a record of
ten miles in 27 minutes, 20 seconds and that the pulling
capacity of a single deer is 1,600 pounds for a distance
of 250 yards. A sled reindeer should make 25 miles a day
for a journey of 100 miles or so, hauling the driver and
50 or 75 pounds, perhaps 300 pounds in all. The reindeer
tire easily in soft snow and must then be frequently rested.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The argument for the use of reindeer is presented by
Carl O. Lind of the Alaska Reindeer Service:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our trip, which demanded 45 days for its accomplishment, was successfully
done before Christmas. In all we traveled about 1,000 miles
under adverse conditions, and four out of seven deer made the return
trip without us, hauling 100 to 200 pounds. If dogs had been used they
could not have hauled their own provisions being picked up by themselves
whenever we stopped. No shelter was needed. When the most furious
wind sweeps its path, the deer simple faces it with an open mouth
and with an expression of satisfaction and joy… It goes uphill
and downhill alike. Trail or no trail, it will haul its 200 pounds or
more day after day; yes, week after week.&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:9&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:9&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;9&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The argument against the use of reindeer has been presented
by the late Archdeacon Stuck:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is not a dog less in Alaska because of the reindeer… Speaking
broadly, the reindeer is a stupid, unwieldy, intractable brute,
not comparing a moment with the dog in intelligence or adaptability…
The rein with which he is driven is a rope tied around
one of his horns. He has no cognizance of “gee” and “haw,” nor
of any other vocal direction, but must be yanked hither and thither
with the rope by main force; while to stop him in his mad career
once he is started it is often necessary to throw him with the rope.&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:10&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:10&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;10&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some use of the Alaskan reindeer as pack animals has been
made, but this mode of employment is not yet well developed.
The large Siberian reindeer will carry 100⁠–⁠150
pounds, but the smaller animal of Alaska will on the average
probably not carry over 50 pounds. The burden is carried
in cloth hampers hung over the animals and made secure
by a lashing going over the back and around the animal’s
belly. Unless thoroughly broken, the pack-bearing animal must be led. There appears to be no question that the pack
reindeer will find a use in the tundra regions where there
is not enough grass to support horses. Its employment
on long journeys has not been tested. Difficulties of herding
when the deer are in pasture present themselves, and as
yet but few reindeer have been broken to the pack.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The evidence in hand shows that the Eskimo reindeer
has clearly demonstrated the fact of the utility of the sled
reindeer to his mode of life. For his purpose the deer is
no doubt more suitable than the dog, for his life is spent
in the tundra region, where reindeer pastures are usually
abundant. On the other hand, experience up to the present
has shown that the needs of winter transport for the whites
can better be served by the dog and the horse than by the
reindeer. As has already be suggested, the value of the
reindeer to both native and white as a source of meat and
hides has been fully demonstrated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is roughly estimated that about 480,000 square miles
of Alaska’s area are, by virtue of the physical condition,
suited for winter dog transport. Of this area, about 220,000
square miles, or less than half, have the physical condition
that makes the use of reindeer practical. This gives a rough
measure of the relative value of the two draft animals; yet,
as has been shown, there are other factors which must
be given consideration in making this comparison.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;water-transport&#34;&gt;Water transport&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Water transportation has been the savior of the province.
Without Alaska’s enormous coast line, aggregating
over twenty thousand miles, and her extensive river systems that
give access, though in part only with great difficulties,
to the most remote parts of the Territory, industrial advancement
would have been impossible. The Alaskan Yukon
and Kuskokwim basins include upwards of five thousand miles
of waters navigable for river steamers. It is these great
arteries of commerce that have served chiefly in the past
to open up the interior to settlement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;hand-powered-craft&#34;&gt;Hand-powered craft&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;https://ettedh.github.io/pics/alaska/raft.webp&#34; alt=&#34;Two men guiding a small raft packed with goods. The man at the back is poling the raft.&#34;/&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Two men crossing a stream on raft. Photo by A. H. Brooks&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Long before any steamers had navigated these rivers,
these waters had been much used for transportation in
various ways. The inland natives of Alaska were, it is
true, a land folk who made relatively little use of the
rivers. Their only boat was a small bark canoe, too frail and light to be used for transport. Downstream journeys
were made by crude rafts and occasionally by a hastily
improvised skin boat made by the stretching of the hide
of a moose or caribou over an ill-constructed framework.
They had, however, no means of transportation upstream,
except the frail canoes which could be pushed against
only a slight current. As has already been shown, the
Russians were indifferent boatmen, and their clumsy river
craft were but ill-adapted to upstream navigation. the
first good river boats in Alaska were those introduced by
the Hudson Bay voyageurs whose boats included both the
double pointed bateaux, using both oars and poles as water
power, and the bark canoes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There were, as has been previously pointed out, no trees
on the Yukon large enough for dugouts and, because of
the small size of the white or canoe birch trees, no possibility
for making practical large bark canoes. Therefore,
the Yukon pioneers were forced to provide boats built of
whipsawed lumber. This common type was a flat-bottomed
boat, sharply pointed at the bow and with a rather narrow
stern, of the general type of a dory, and some 18–24
feet long. Later the Yukon poling boat was devised. This
was a long, narrow, tapering craft, admirably adapted to
upstream journeys, against swift current and in shallow
water. The poling boat was 20⁠–⁠30 feet long, and amidships,
its bottom measured from 12 to 20 inches with
tapering sides, giving it 2½⁠–⁠3 feet of
beam at the gunwale. Though tapering rapidly at both
ends, it is usually built with snub nose at both bow and
stern. The Yukon poling boat was no doubt an adaptation
of similar types of craft long used on the western rivers.
Up to the time of the use of steamers, the Ohio River keelboats,
said to have been first used in 1793, with their
expert polers were the only crafts which would go upstream.
These Ohio River boats were 50 feet long, but
only 12⁠–⁠15 feet wide, and were propelled by ten polemen.
Their form and mode of use were identical with the
Mississippi craft.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is surprising with what facility good polemen can push a loaded boat of this type up swift streams and with
barely enough depth of water to float the craft. With fair
conditions two good men could take a ton of supplies upstream
at the rate of 10⁠–⁠20 miles a day, and with a
lighter load. 30 miles a day were not uncommon. In the
early days of Yukon mining it was not infrequent for a
party of men to make the journey from Fortymile to
Lake Lindeman, the head of boat navigation, a distance
of nearly 600 miles, in a month, an average speed of nearly
20 miles a day. This included the time spent in making
the difficult portage around White Horse Rapids and Miles
Canyon, and also the easy navigation of Laberge and other
lakes of the upper Lewes River.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;https://ettedh.github.io/pics/alaska/eskimo-tracking.webp&#34; alt=&#34;Man toeing a boat on a riverbank. To his side is a dog. Behind the man, the bank has a ridge.&#34;/&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;An Eskimo &#34;tracking,&#34; photo by A. H. Brooks&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In these upstream journeys propulsion by poling was
varied by &lt;i&gt;tracking&lt;/i&gt;. This consisted in dragging the boat
by lines of men walking on the shore. By attaching two
lines to the boat, the men can readily steer it from the
shore; and if good footing can be obtained, they can drag
half a ton or more of supplies upstream at the rate of ten
miles or more a day. Where the stream is shallow and the
current swift, much wading is usually necessary to ease
the boat over the bars. Where there are steep-cut banks
and the water is too deep to pole, the boat must be pulled
by the bushes and trees along the banks. This method of
propulsion, formerly called “bushwhacking” on the Ohio
River, is slow and tedious; and a whole day may be consumed
to advance a few miles. It is not uncommon to use
dogs as draft animals in taking boats up streams.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was the Canadian explorers like William Ogilvie who
first introduced the &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Peterborough_Canoe_Company&#34;&gt;Peterborough canoes&lt;/a&gt; on the Yukon;
and later, this craft was much used by the Northwest
Mounted Police. Just as the poling boat has been the craft
of the prospector, so the canoe has been the craft of the
explorer. In general modeled after the Ojibwe bark canoe,
the Peterborough is an admirable swift water boat, carries
a large cargo, and is so light that it can be portaged a
long distance. This model is built in sizes varying from 17
to 24 feet in length with a beam of 40⁠–⁠52 inches. The
favorite canoe of the explorer is about 19 feet long and 46
inches wide. Such a boat built of cedar will, when dry,
weigh about 120 pounds, and in an emergency can be packed
by a single man across a portage. It will safely carry a
cargo of half a ton besides a crew of two or three men.
With a fair wind it makes a fairly good sailing craft.
When it is equipped with six-foot paddles, ten-foot poles,
and good tracking lines, there are no inland waters navigable
to any other craft on which a Peterborough canoe
can not be used. I have used a Peterborough provided with
a small coaming and canvas air-tight compartments
in fairly heavy weather on the Bering Sea. In river navigation,
punctures by snags or rocks of thin cedar planking
are not uncommon, but these are quickly and permanently
repaired by strips carried for the purpose. The Geological
Survey in the course of its explorations and investigations
in Alaska has used these canoes on about fifteen thousand miles of
the watercourses of Alaska. During the Klondike rush,
when every type of craft was used, folding canoes and
boats were not uncommon. Though easier to portage than
Peterboroughs, they are useless for upstream work, being
too flimsy to buck a current. They have found use in
explorations, because they can be packed on a horse and
transported overland and they are a necessity for cruising
rivers too deep to ford, the banks of which are untimbered.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;engine-powered-craft&#34;&gt;Engine-powered craft&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The introduction of the light portable gas engine has
greatly modified Alaskan water travel. Many prospectors
avoid the labor of poling and tracking by its use. In
shallow rivers air propellors have been successfully used.
Nearly every Yukon Indian now has some sort of gas boat
to visit his &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fish_wheel&#34;&gt;fish wheels&lt;/a&gt; and to travel from place to place.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Coastal navigation has also been completely revolutionized
during the past two decades by the gas engines.
Previous to 1900, the prospector and the fisherman traveled
chiefly in crafts propelled by sail and oars, but now the
use of power boats is almost universal. The favorite craft
is the Columbia River fishing boat, 20⁠–⁠30 feet long, of
the lifeboat type, and admirable for heavy weather. These,
formerly propelled solely by sail and oars, are now equipped
with economical heavyweight gas engines.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Western Union Telegraph exploring expeditions had
for part of their project the steam navigation of the Yukon
River. Two flat-bottomed boats about 60 feet long, the
&lt;i&gt;Wilder&lt;/i&gt; and the &lt;i&gt;Lizzie Horner&lt;/i&gt;, were shipped to Saint Michael
in 1866, but neither succeeded in entering the mouth of
the Yukon. Navigation of the Yukon continued by small
boat until the newly organized Alaska Commercial Company
brought in its first small steamer, the &lt;i&gt;Yukon&lt;/i&gt;. This
boat was 50 feet long with 12-foot beams, was equipped
with two engines, and drew when loaded 18 inches of water;
it was built by John W. Gates of San Francisco. On July 4,
1869, with Captain Benjamin Hall as master and John R.
Forbes as engineer, the &lt;i&gt;Yukon&lt;/i&gt; left Saint Michael and 27
days later arrived at Fort Yukon, having completed the
ferst steam navigation of the lower thousand miles of the
Yukon River. Within the next ten years, three other small
steamers were brought to the Yukon and navigated the
river up as far as Fort Selkirk,&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:11&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:11&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;11&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; 1,700 miles from the Bering
Sea. These boats were chiefly used in the fur trade, but
they also supplied the few prospectors then in the region.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;https://ettedh.github.io/pics/alaska/ss-scotia.webp&#34; alt=&#34;A steamboat docked next to massive piles of logs&#34;/&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&#34;S.S. Scotia&#34; taking on wood on Taku Arm, photo by Sidney Page&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With the influx of miners after the discovery of gold
in the Fortymile district, a larger vessel was demanded.
In 1889, the Alaska Commercial Company built the &lt;i&gt;Arctic&lt;/i&gt;,&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:12&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:12&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;12&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;
140 feet in length with a 28-foot beam. By this time the
annual freight taken up the Yukon was largely the trading
goods and provisions to supply the Alaska Commercial
Company posts. Freight charges to the upper river were
$50 a ton, passenger rates $150. The freight rates were
very reasonable, and the passenger rates affected but few
of the miners, who arrived mostly by the Chilkoot Pass
route. In 1892, the North American Trading and Transportation
Company entered the Yukon as a rival in fur
trade and transportation. Their first boat, the &lt;i&gt;Portner B.
Ware&lt;/i&gt;, of about the same size as the &lt;i&gt;Arctic&lt;/i&gt;, ascended the
Yukon for some 200 miles in September, but was frozen in
before it reached the mining camps. The organization of
this company was due to the energy of J. J. Healy, a pioneer
Alaska fur trader. He long maintained a trading post at
Dyea, the gateway of Chilkoot Pass, and from information
obtained from the miners became convinced of the industrial
importance of the Yukon. As the managing head
of a great commercial company, he was a commanding
figure on the Yukon during the Klondike days, but he died
a pauper in 1910.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With the Klondike rush came an enormous expansion
of Yukon River traffic. In 1898 and 1899, between 75 and
100 steam-driven vessels were plowing the muddy waters
of the great river and its tributaries. In 1900, five transportation
companies were operating 33 river boats on the
Alaskan Yukon, and a dozen steamboats were navigating
the Canadian waters above. There is no record of the
traffic during the height of the Klondike travel; but in
1901, when it had greatly subsided, 35 boats carried 25,000
tons of freight up the Yukon, and the passenger traffic
upstream and downstream aggregated 2,500 persons. This
was at a time when the building of the White Pass &amp;amp;
Yukon Railroad had, by establishing, a through freight and
passenger service from Skagway, greatly reduced the traffic
on the lower river. The tariffs were, in 1901, $85 a ton for
freight and $125 a passenger, from Saint Michael to Dawson.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During this period, large packets were built for the
Yukon service,&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:13&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:13&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;13&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; comparable to those used on the Mississippi.
Their masters and pilots were recruited from the Mississippi
and Columbia rivermen, the former having the prestige
of having operated large boats, the latter being more
experienced in handling steamers in swift water. The
large steamers had lengths of 222 feet, beams of 42 feet,
depths of 6 feet, and horsepower of 1,000. For many
years they were all wood burners, for the several attempts
to use the local lignitic coal were unsuccessful.&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:14&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:14&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;14&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; In 1906,
many of the boats were changed to oil burners, the petroleum
being brought from California. These large packets
proved to be uneconomical, and there has been a gradual
change to smaller boats of from 400 to 600 tons which
could be efficiently used on the small tributaries of the
Yukon. With the decrease of gold mining, steamer traffic
has already decreased. In 1919, only nine steamers were
operated in the Alaskan Yukon, carrying a total of less
than 10,000 tons of freight.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In general, the Yukon is open to navigation from June
until October. The ice-free season, however, varies in different
parts of the basin. Above Dawson, the river is
usually clear of ice soon after the middle of May, and
steamers can be operated well into October. Navigation
on the lower Yukon is possible from the last week in May
until the end of September. The ice, however, often does
not go out of the Yukon delta until July, and the river
there may be frozen again by the middle of September.
One reason for the high freight rate on the Yukon is that
the expensive equipment and, to a certain extent, the
personnel too are idle for eight to nine months in the year.
All the profits must be made during the short season of
navigation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;roads&#34;&gt;Roads&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nothing emphasizes the slow growth of means of transportation
in Alaska more than the history of its road construction.
The Russians during nearly a century of occupation
built less than five miles of wagon road in the
American possessions. During the next thirty years, up to
the time of the Klondike gold discovery, we added barely
another five miles to the total length of wagon road. At
the fiftieth anniversary of the annexation of Alaska, there
were only 980 miles of wagon road in the Territory,&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:15&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:15&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;15&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; an
area of nearly six hundred thousand square miles and a population then
of nearly seventy thousand. At this time, the Government had spent
a total of $3,970,000 on road and trail construction in
local taxes. Alaska had in turn produced minerals, fish
and fur up to a total value of $800,000,000. It is questionable
whether any other one country in the world has shown such a notable industial advancement with such a scant
outlay of public funds for transportation facilities.&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:16&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:16&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;16&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;private-construction&#34;&gt;Private construction&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;https://ettedh.github.io/pics/alaska/early-roads-i.webp&#34; alt=&#34;Two photos side by side. The left shows a man standing on a rut trail in the woods. The right shows a man standing on a trail with wagon ruts carved into deep snow.&#34;/&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;b&gt;Early roads, I.&lt;/b&gt; These roads were frequently crude affairs as is shown by the wagon road (left) up Gold Creek and that to the Jualin Mine in the Berners Bay district (right).&lt;br /&gt; Photos by C. W. Wright.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A little construction and some improvements of roads at
Sitka were done by the military authorities between 1867
and 1877, but beyond this bit, there was no building of
roads until after the discovery of the Juneau gold. In
1882, a horse trail was built by the miners for two miles
up Gold Creek, and later this was changed to a wagon
road which, by 1888, had been extended into the Silver
Bow basin. The building of this road in part through a
steep-walled valley was an expensive undertaking and all
of it was paid for by local mining industry. In 1898, a
law was passed, authorizing the construction and maintenance
of toll roads and bridges in Alaska,&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:17&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:17&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;17&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; a privilege
of which, however, few availed themselves. The Chilkat
Indians had long regarded the Chilkoot Pass trail as a toll
road owned by them, a monopoly which the pioneer miners
soon disregarded and claimed the right of carrying their
own burdens over it without charge. When the Klondike
rush started, a wagon road was constructed from tidewater
at Dyea for eight miles to the entrance of the canyon, and
during the height of the travel it carried on a brisk business.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the spring of 1898, George A. Bracket completed fifteen
miles of wagon road from Skagway to the base of the final
steep thousand-foot climb leading to the summit of the White
Pass. This road traversed the heavily timbered flat of
Skagway River for some five miles, and beyond led along
the precipitous slopes of a rocky defile. At that time, the
Bracket road was the longest and most difficult piece of
highway construction that had been attempted in Alaska.
Remnants of this pioneer road are still visible from the
White Pass &amp;amp; Yukon Railroad where they can be seen
clinging to the sides of precipitous cliffs. Bracket’s troubles,
however, did not end with the building of the road, for he
found it difficult to collect the toll of $20 a ton to which he
was legally entitled. Many Klodikers could see no reason
for paying toll on a route through which they had had a
sled trail before the building of the road. Some of the
toll collectors were roughly handled. But the controversy
over toll was short-lived, for by May of 1898 the railroad
surveyors had arrived and the railroad company bought
the wagon road,&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:18&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:18&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;18&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; both for the prevention of competition in
the haulage of freight and for hauling use in construction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jack Dalton, in 1898, built a horse trail from Pyramid
Harbor on Lynn Canal to the top of the pass at the head
of Klehini River. This opened up a route into the interior
well suited for horses and cattle which Dalton had explored.
No trail work was necessary beyond the pass where the
country was open. Dalton himself drove in several herd
of beef cattle and horses, reaching the Yukon either at
Five Finger Rapids or at Fort Selkirk at the mouth of the
Pelly. The Dalton trail was the best pack horse route into
the interior, but it was not much used even before the
completion of the railroad and the venture was not a
financial success.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In addition to the above, a few toll bridges have been
built at various places in Alaska. On the whole, however,
the toll road and bridge act of 1898 was entirely ineffective
in opening up Alaska.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;public-construction&#34;&gt;Public construction&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 1904, Congress made a second attempt to provide
roads for Alaska without appropriating any funds. This
effort compelled the United States commissioners to appoint
a road overseer in each district, who was to receive the
magnificent wage of $4 a day, the average wage at that
time being $6 to $10 a day. Recognizing that the poor
overseers would be at a financial loss for every day of
employment, the law specified that they were to be paid
for only ten days in the year. In this time these philanthropists
were not only to construct roads but also to notify
every man in their district that they must give two days’
work to road building each year, or in lieu thereof, to pay
a head tax of $8. This law was evidently framed on the
ancient statutes of many of the Eastern states, by which
road building was made the duty of every citizen, and a
knowledge of road engineering was recognized to be inborn
in every American. For generations, this ancient fallacy
hampered the development of good roads, and it was done
away with only after the inauguration of modern highway
construction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No fault can be found with the principle of the Alaska
Road Act of 1904, of throwing the burden of road construction
on the Territory. But this should have been done
by a proper system of local taxes, and the funds collected
spent by qualified engineers. In Canadian territory, this
was recognized from the start, and the royalty collected on
the Klondike paid for the excellent system of highways
in the Yukon Territory. The Alaskan law was almost
futile in providing means of communication, though a few
local sled roads and trais were improved, most of which
were badly located and poorly constructed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The extensive federal exploration of Alaska inaugurated
in 1898, chiefly by the Geological Survey and, for the first
few years, by the Army, included many long journeys.
Many of these exploring expeditions used horses and, incidental
to their advance, many miles of rough trail were
established. These were subsequently followed by others
and, in lieu of better trails, became established as routes
of travel. A few are still in use, and we still hear of the
&lt;i&gt;Gem Trail&lt;/i&gt;, and the &lt;i&gt;Survey&lt;/i&gt; and &lt;i&gt;Army&lt;/i&gt; trails. Far
more important than these trails to betterment of means
of communication were the maps and reports which resulted
from the work of these expeditions. All had as
part of their mission the location of possible routes for
wagon roads and railroads. The actual areal mapping fell
chiefly to the Geological Survey which, before the epoch
of road and railroad construction that began some five
years later was inaugurated, had made contoured reconnaissance
maps of nearly all the routes which were subsequently
chosen or considered for wagon roads or railroads.
This work admirably furnishes conclusive proof
of the value of topographic maps. The cost of the areal
topographic surveys of Alaska has been far less than it
would have been had it been necessary to carry out explorations
for every road and railroad project. These maps gave
information on the best general route, and it was only
necessary for the engineer to make his location survey.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many of the reports of this exploring expedition made
more or less definite recommendations for road and trail
construction. For example, in 1903, incidental to the discussion
of the future of placer mining,&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:19&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:19&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;19&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; I recommended
that a million dollars be spent in building wagon roads to
the inland placer camps. The recommendation included a
road from Valdez to Eagle or Fairbanks as a main highway
and many other local roads. The opinion was then expressed
that several of the Yukon gold camps had probably
already spent more money in the transport of supplies
than the cost of wagon roads. This was probably an exaggeration,
but that such a generous project for wagon
roads was sound is proved by the fact that most of those
it included have, during the twenty years that have since
elapsed, been completed or are under construction.&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:20&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:20&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;20&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;https://ettedh.github.io/pics/alaska/bridge.webp&#34; alt=&#34;A simple wooden truss bridge crossing a stream of about twenty feet&#34;/&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;The backpackers will probably cross an old-fashioned bridge (photo by F. H. Moffit)&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Though the trails established by these early exploring
expeditions were of use to the prospector, they were little
more than cuts through the timber, with here and there
some small bridges. The only actual trail construction by
such an expedition was that built under the direction of
Major W. R. Abercrombie, from Valdez inland. Abercrombie,
commanding the Copper River expedition of the
U.S. Army, landed at Valdez in the spring of 1898. His
parties, as already noted in Chapter 16,&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref1:7&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:7&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; subsequently
made their way inland over the difficult an dangerous
Valdez Glacier route and also explored other passes through
the coastal mountain barrier. Abercrombie recommended
that a military trail be built inland from Valdez by a
route which would avoid the glacier. This was authorized
in 1899, and during the summer, Abercrombie constructed
a horse trail to the summit of Thompson Pass, thus surmounting
the most serious obstacle to inland travel. During
the following five years a crude pack trail was built through
to Eagle on the Yukon, under appropriations granted by
the War Department. Good service was rendered the pioneers
by this trail, but its construction is chiefly significant
in being a forerunner of splendid work done by the
Army in road construction in Alaska.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since the law of 1904 was found futile in opening up
Alaska, a new statute was enacted in 1906. This provided
for an Alaska Road Commission of three Army officers,
one to be detailed from the Corps of Engineers. This board
was authorized to construct and maintain military and
post roads, bridges, and trails from funds collected by the
existing license taxes outside of incorporated towns. Thirty
percent of these taxes was reserved for maintenance of
schools for whites, and 25 percent for care of the insane;
the remainder was to be used for road construction and to
this was added a direct appropriation of $150,000. This
law marked the real beginning of road construction in
Alaska, and its beneficial effects have been felt throughout
the Territory ever since its enactment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The original act left but little to to be desired. Its immediate
and continued success, however, was almost entirely due
to the fact that Brigadier General (then Major) Wilds P.
Richardson, a man of exceptional executive ability, was
chosen to be president of the board and continued in this
office until 1917 when he recalled for military duty.
At the time of his detail, General Richardson had had eight
years of almost continuous service in the Territory, during
which time he had pioneered on the Yukon, built trails, and
established Army posts. These duties had given him a
broad knowledge of Alaska and her people, and his duties
in road location and construction soon made him the leading
authority on the subject of Alaskan transportation. His
duties and responsibilities were arduous; for not only had
he to carry on road building under very adverse physical
conditions, but also he had to meet constant criticisms from
local residents who could not realize that an annual grant
of only a few hundred thousand dollars could not begin to
meet the needs for wagon roads.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Richardson was quick to grasp that the crux of the transportation
problem was to establish a trunk line of communication
between open waters on the Pacific and the
inland region. He, therefore, almost at once established a
sled road between Valdez on the coast and Fairbanks, the
largest settlement in the interior, a distance of 370 miles.
Year by year, this route was improved, and it passed by
successive stages, from dog trail, to sled road, to wagon road,
and finally to a fair automobile road. For years, this was a
main artery of mail routes and passenger trail into the
interior, and it has only recently been superseded by the
completion of the government railroad. Richardson’s vision
extended even further, for he conceived the bold project
of an extension of this road through to Nome, thus giving
an overland route to this remote community. This larger
project he unfortunately could not carry out because of lack
of funds. In addition to the main highway, now known
appropriately as the Richardson Road, many local roads
and trails were also built.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Richardson’s many years of service devoted to the interests
of Alaska are one of the outstanding features of
federal administration of Territorial affairs. After his
return to military duty, his work was most efficiently continued
by the officers of the Engineer Corps to whom the
task was assigned. By 1920, the Commission had built
4,890 miles of road and trail, of which 1,031 miles were
wagon road. There had been expended in construction and
maintenance a total of $5,498,000, of which $3,370,000 were
from direct appropriations and the rest from local taxes.
Meanwhile, some roads and trail had been built by the
Forest Service and by the Territorial Road Commission.&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:21&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:21&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;21&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;
Thus great progress has been made, but the industrial needs
of the Territory demand at least an equal mileage of roads
and trails to that already constructed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the most important acts of Congress for the
benefit of Alaska was the authorizing in 1900 of military
cable connection with Alaskan ports, the establishment of
land telegraph lines, and wireless stations. The original
act was passed, largely through the personal efforts of
Major General A. W. Greely, then chief signal officer.
Thanks to Greely’s efforts, cable communication with
Juneau and other Alaskan ports was established by 1903,
and by that time land lines had been extended over much
of the inland region.&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:22&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:22&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;22&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Later, all important Alaskan towns
were given some from of electrical communication cable:
telegraph, telephone, or wireless.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first aids to navigation in Alaskan waters were fourteen
buoys placed in Peril Strait in 1906.&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:23&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:23&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;23&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; The hundreds of
vessels which traversed Alaskan waters during the Klondike
excitement, carrying thousands of passengers and millions
of dollars worth of freight, were transported through
these dangerous waters with hardly a single aid to navigation.
The losses of ships in Alaskan waters have been
appalling. These were in part, of course, due to the natural
physical conditions; but they are chargeable also to the
lack of sufficient aids to navigation and the lack of adequate
charts, a problem which the Coast Survey, with its
very limited facilities,&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:24&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:24&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;24&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; has tried hard to meet. Alaska’s
vast shore line still has only one life-saving station, which
was established at Nome in 1905. The Revenue Cutter
Service, now the Coast Guard, has, however, from the beginning
of its cruises in northern waters rendered much
aid to wrecked vessels and has been the means of saving
many lives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnotes&#34;&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:1&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ed.: This essay was seemingly written some time between 1920 and Brook’s death in 1924.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:2&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cf. “Railroad Routes in Alaska.” &lt;i&gt;Report of Alaska Railroad Commission, and Congress, 3rd session, H. R. Doc. 1346&lt;/i&gt;, 1913, pp. 114⁠–⁠130.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:3&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Russians had only small coastal vessels driven by steam, their trans-Pacific traffic being all by sailing vessels.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:4&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;C. L. Andrews, “&lt;a href=&#34;https://journals.lib.washington.edu/index.php/WHQ/article/view/5421&#34;&gt;Marine Disasters of the Alaska Route&lt;/a&gt;,” &lt;i&gt;Washington Historical Quarterly&lt;/i&gt;, 7, no. 1 (1916): 24⁠–⁠37.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:4&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:5&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 1878, the entire expenditure for the Alaskan mail service was $18,000, which provided monthly service to Sitka and Wrangell. By 1898, only seven post offices had been established in the Territory. In 1920, there was a total of 159 post offices of all classes.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:5&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:6&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A speed of nine miles an hour for four hours has been recorded in some of the dog races.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:6&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:7&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;See Alfred H. Brooks, &lt;i&gt;Blazing Alaska&amp;rsquo;s Trails&lt;/i&gt; (University of Alaska Press, 1953).&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:7&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref1:7&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:8&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;D. H. Jarvis, &lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.loc.gov/resource/gdcmassbookdig.reportofcruiseof03unit/?sp=89&#34;&gt;Report of the Cruise of the U.S. Revenue Cutter Bear and the Overland Relief Expedition&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/i&gt;. Washington: Government Printing Office, 1899. p. 47.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:8&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:9&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sheldon Jackson, &lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://hdl.handle.net/2027/coo.31924070856780&#34;&gt;Fourteenth Annual Report on the Introduction Domestic Reindeer into Alaska&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/i&gt; (Washington, D.C., 1906), pp. 104–105.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:9&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:10&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hudson Stuck, &lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://catalog.hathitrust.org/Record/007706307&#34;&gt;Ten Thousand Miles with a Dog Sled&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/i&gt; (New York, 1914), p. 402, 407.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:10&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:11&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first trip above Fort Yukon, made in 1875, ascended the Yukon as far as the site of Fort Reliance, about six miles below Dawson.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:11&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:12&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;i&gt;Arctic&lt;/i&gt; brought the first cargo of provisions to the then newly-discovered Klondike in the fall of 1896, but soon was caught in the ice and wrecked.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:12&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:13&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gross tonnage, 800 to 1,211.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:13&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:14&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During the Klondike days, wood for steamers was sold at $15 and $25 a cord, but the normal price is $4 to $8.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:14&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:15&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In addition, there were 620 miles of winter sled road and 250 miles of improved trail.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:15&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:16&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Government railroad construction at this time was beginning to rectify matters.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:16&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:17&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The law provided that the toll rates must be approved by the Secretary of the Interior.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:17&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:18&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The price paid for the wagon road was $40,000.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:18&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:19&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alfred H. Brooks, “Placer Mining in Alaska,” &lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://lccn.loc.gov/2003216166&#34;&gt;United States Geological Survey Bulletin&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/i&gt;, no. 225, Washington, D.C., 1904, pp. 56⁠–⁠57.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:19&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:20&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is worthy of note that C. W. Purington, then of the Geological Survey, was the first to present definite estimates of the cost of road construction in Alaska and to substantiate by actual figures their need to the placer mining industry. See his “Roads and Road Building in Alaska,” Ibid., no. 263 (1905). pp. 217⁠–⁠228.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:20&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:21&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is estimated that the cost of wagon road construction in Alaska at the prices of 1920 will be from $5,000 to $6,000 a mile.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:21&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:22&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It should be remembered that the Western Union Telegraph Company built and operated some fifteen miles of telegraph line in Seward Peninsula as early as 1867. The construction of long distance private telephone lines was begun at Nome in 1900, but telephones had by then been in use for a number of years at Juneau. Nearly all Alaskan towns of over 400 population have a telephone system.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:22&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:23&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Russians had one lighthouse in Alaska. This was a light placed in the cupola of the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nps.gov/places/baranof-castle-state-historic-site.htm&#34;&gt;Baranof Castle&lt;/a&gt; at Sitka. It was maintained by the Army for a few years after the annexation and then abandoned because of lack of funds.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:23&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:24&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 1920, about ten percent of Alaskan waters had been charted in the detail needed for navigation.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:24&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
	</item>
	
	<item>
		<title>Letters of Vesuvius</title>
		<link>https://ettedh.github.io/texts/vesuvius/</link>
		<pubDate>Sat, 22 Mar 2025 19:54:22 -0500</pubDate>
		
		<guid>https://ettedh.github.io/texts/vesuvius/</guid>
		<description>&lt;p&gt;These texts are modified from the Loeb 1915 version of Pliny&amp;rsquo;s &lt;i xml:lang=&#34;la&#34;&gt;Epistulae&lt;/i&gt;&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, letters 16 and 20 from Book 6.&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:2&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;first-letter-to-tacitus&#34;&gt;First letter to Tacitus&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Your request that I would send you an account of my uncle&amp;rsquo;s end, so that you may transmit a more exact relation of it to posterity, deserves my acknowledgements; for if his death shall be celebrated by your pen, the glory of it, I am aware, will be rendered for ever deathless. For notwithstanding he perished, as did whole peoples and cities, in the destruction of a most beautiful region, and by a misfortune memorable enough to promise him a kind of immortality: notwithstanding he has, himself, composed many and lasting work⁠—I am persuaded that the mentioning of him in your immortal writings will greatly contribute to eternize his name. Happy I esteem those, whom Providence has gifted with the ability, either to do things worthy of being written, or to write in a manner worthy of being read; but most happy they, who are blessed with both talents, in which latter class, my uncle will be placed both by his own writings and by yours. The more willingly do I undertake⁠—nay, solicit⁠—the task you set me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He was, at that time, with the fleet under his command at Misenum. On the ninth day before the Kalends of September,&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:3&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; about one in the afternoon, my mother desired him to observe a cloud of very unusual size and appearance.  He had sunned himself, then taken a cold bath, and after a leisurely luncheon, was engaged in study. He immediately called for his shoes and went up an eminence, from whence he might best view this very uncommon appearance. It was not at that distance discernible from what mountain this cloud issued, but it was found afterwards to be Vesuvius. I cannot give you a more exact description of its figure, than by resembling it to that of a pinetree, for it shot up a great height in the form of a trunk, which extended itself at the top into several branches; because I imagine, a momentary gust of air blew it aloft, and then failing, forsook it; thus causing the cloud to expand laterally as it dissolved, or possibly the downward pressure of its own weight produced this effect. It was at one moment white, at another dark and spotted, as if it had carried up earth or cinders.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My uncle, true savant that he was, deemed the phenomenon important and worth a nearer view.  He ordered a light vessel to be got ready, and gave me the liberty, if I thought proper, to attend him.  I replied that I would rather study; and, as it happened, he himself had given me a theme for composition.  As he was coming out of the house he received a note from Rectina, the wife of Bassus, who was in the utmost alarm at the imminent danger (his villa stood just below us, and there was no way to escape but by sea); she earnestly entreated him to save her from such deadly peril. He changed his first design and what he began with a philosophical, he pursued with an heroical, turn of mind. He ordered large galleys to be launched, and went himself on board one, with the intention of assisting not only Rectina, but many others; for the villas stand extremely thick upon that beautiful coast. Hastening to the place from whence others were flying, he steered his direct course to the point of danger, and with such freedon from fear, as to be able to make and dictate his observations upon the successive motions and figures of that terrific object.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And now cinders, which grew thicker and hotter the nearer he approached, fell into the ships, then pumice-stones too, with stones blackened, scorched, and cracked by fire, then the sea ebbed suddenly from under them, while the shore was blocked up by landslips from the mountains. After considering for a moment whether he should retreat, he said to the captain who was urging that course, &amp;ldquo;Fortune favors the bold; carry me to Pomponianus.&amp;rdquo;  Pomponianus was then at Stabiae, distant by half the width of the bay (for, as you know, the shore, insensibly curving in its sweep, forms here a vessel for the sea). He had already embarked his baggage; for thougn at Stabiae the danger was not yet near, it was fully in view, and certain to be extremely near, as soon as it spread; and he resolved to fly as soon as the contrary wind should cease. It was fully favorable, however, for carrying my uncle to Pomponianus. He embraces, comforts, and encourages his alarmed friend, and in order to soothe the other’s fears by his own unconcern, desires to be conducted to a bathroon; and, after having bathed, he sat down to supper with great cheerfulness, or at least (what is equally heroic) with all the appearance of it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the meanwhile, Mount Vesuvius was blazing in several places, with spreading and towering flames, whose radiant brightness the darkness of the night set in high relief. But, my uncle, in order to soothe apprehensions, kept saying that some fires had been left alight by the terrified country people, and what they saw were only deserted villas on fire in the abandoned district. After, this he retired to rest, and it is most certain that his rest was a most genuine slumber; for his breathing, which, as he was pretty fat, was somewhat heavy and sonorous, was heard by those who attended his chamber-door. But the court which led to his apartment now lay so deep under a mixture of pumice-stones and ashes, that if he had continued longer in his bedroom, exiting would have been impossible. After being awakened, he came out, and returned to Pomponianus and the others, who had sat up all night. They consulted together as to whether they should hold out in the house, or to wander about in the open. For the house now tottered under repeated and violent concussions, and seemed to rock to and fro as if torn from its foundations. In the open air, on the other hand, they dreaded the falling pumice-stones, light and porous though they were; yet this, by comparison, seemed the lesser danger of the two; a conclusion which my uncle arrived at by balancing reasons, and the others by balancing fears. They tied pillows upon their heads with napkins; and this was their whole defense against the showers that fell round them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was now day everywhere else, but there, a deeper darkness prevailed than in the most obscure night; relieved, however, by many torches and different lights. They thought it proper to go down to the shore to observe from close at-hand, if they could possibly put out to sea, but they found the waves still running extremely high and contrary.  There, my uncle, having thrown himself down upon a disused sail, repeatedly called for, and drank, an amount of cold water; soon after, flames, and a strong smell of sulphur⁠—which was the forerunner of them⁠—dispersed the rest of the company in flight; and only roused him. He raised himself up with the assistance of two of his slaves, but instantly fell; some unusually-gross vapor, as I conjecture, having obstructed his breathing and blocked his windpipe, which was not only naturally weak and constricted, but chronically inflamed. When day dawned again (the third day from the last he had seen) his body was found entire and uninjured, and still fully-clothed as in life; its posture was that of a sleeping, rather than a dead man.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, my mother and I were at Misenum.  But this has no connection with history, and your inquiry went no farther than concerning my uncle’s death. I will, therefore, put an end to my letter.  Suffer me only to add, that I have faithfully related to you what I was either an eye-witness of myself, or heard at the time, when report speaks most true.  You will select what is most suitable to your purpose; for there is a great difference between a letter, and a history; between writing to a friend, and writing for the public. Farewell.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;second-letter-to-tacitus&#34;&gt;Second letter to Tacitus&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The letter which, in compliance with your request, I wrote to you concerning the death of my uncle, has raised your curiosity, you say, to know not only what terrors, but what calamities I endured when left behind at Misenum (for there I broke off my narrative)?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Though my mind shudders to remember,⁠&amp;hellip; I will begin.&amp;rdquo;&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:4&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:4&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My uncle having set out, I gave the rest of the day to study⁠—the object which had kept me at home.  After which, I bathed, dined, and retired to short and broken slumbers. There had been, for several days before, some shocks of earthquake, which alarmed us less, as they are frequent in Campania; but that night, they became so violent that one might think that the world was not being merely shaken, but turned topsy-turvy. My mother flew to my chamber; I was just rising, meaning on my part to awaken her if she was asleep. We sat down in the forecourt of the house, which separated it by a short space from the sea. I do not know whether I should call it courage or inexperience⁠—I was not quite eighteen⁠—but I called for a volume of Livy, and began to read, and even went on with the extracts I was making from it, as if nothing were the matter.  Lo and behold, a friend of my uncle&amp;rsquo;s, who had just come to him from Spain, appears on the scene; observing my mother and me seated, and the fact that I have a book in my hand, he sharply censures her patience and my indifference; nevertheless, I still went on intently with my author.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was now six o’clock in the morning, the light still ambiguous and faint. The buildings around us already tottered, and though we stood upon open ground, as the place was narrow and confined, there was certain and formidable danger of them collapsing. It was not till then we resolved to quit the town. The common people follow us in the utmost consternation, preferring the judgement of others to their own (wherein the extreme of fear resembles prudence), and force us onwards by pressing a crowd in on our rears. Having arrived outside the houses, we halt in the midst of a most strange and dreadful scene. The coaches which we had ordered out, though stood upon the most level ground, were sliding to and fro, and could not be kept steady even when stones were put against the wheels. Then we beheld the sea sucked back, and as it were repulsed by the convulsive motion of the earth; it is at least certain than the shore was considerably enlarged, and now held many sea animals captive on the dry sand.  On the other side, a black and dreadful cloud, bursting out in gusts of igneous, serpentine vapor, now and again yawned open to reveal long, fantastic flames, resembling flashes of lightning, but much larger.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our Spanish friend already mentioned now spoke with more warmth and instancy: “If your brother⁠— if your uncle,” said he, “is still alive, he wishes you both to be safe; if he has perished, it was his desire that you would survive him. Why therefore do you delay your escape?” &lt;i&gt;We could never think of our own safety,&lt;/i&gt; we said, &lt;i&gt;while we are uncertain of his.&lt;/i&gt; Without further ado, our friend hurried off, and took himself out of danger at the top of his speed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Soon afterwards, the cloud I have described began to descend upon the earth, and cover the sea. It had already encircled the hidden Capreae, and blotted from sight the promontory of Misenum. My mother now began to beseech, exhort, and command me to escape as best I might; a young man could do it; she, burdened with age and corpulency, would die easy if only she had not caused my death. I replied, I would not be saved without her, and taking her by the hand, I hurried her on. She complies reluctantly and not without reproaching herself for delaying me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ashes now fall upon us, though as yet in no great quantity. I looked behind me; great darkness pressed on our rears, and came rolling over the land after us like a torrent. I proposed while we still could see, to turn aside, lest we should be knocked down into the road by the crowd that followed us, and trampled to death in the dark. We had scarce sat down, when darkness spread over us⁠—not like that of a moonless or cloudy night, but of a room when it is shut up, and the lamp put out. You could hear the shrieks of women, the crying of children, and the shouts of men; some were seeking their children, others their parents, others their wives, or husbands, and only distinguishing them by their voices; one lamenting his own fate, another that of his family; some praying to die, from the very fear of dying; many lifting their hands to the gods; but the greater part, imagining that there were no gods left anywhere, and that the last and eternal night had come upon the world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There were even some who augmented the real perils by imaginary terrors. Newcomers reported that such-and-such a building at Misenum had collapsed or taken fire⁠—falsely, but they were credited. By degrees it grew lighter; which we imagined to be rather the warning of approaching fire (as in truth it was) than the return of day: however, the fire stayed at a distance from us: then again came darkness, and a heavy shower of ashes; we were obliged every now and then to rise and shake them off, otherwise we should have been buried and even crushed under their weight. I might have boasted, that amidst dangers so appalling, not a sigh or expression of fear escaped from me, had not my support been founded in that miserable though strong consolation, that all mankind were involved in the same calamity, and that I was perishing with the world itself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At last, this dreadful darkness was attenuated by degrees to a kind of cloud or smoke, and passed away; presently the real day returned, and even the sun appeared, though pale as when an eclipse is in progress. Every object that presented itself to our yet-affrighted gaze was changed, covered over with a drift of ashes, as with snow. We returned to Misenum, where we refreshed ourselves as well as we could, and passed an anxious night between hope and fear⁠—though indeed with a much larger share of the latter, for the earthquake still continued, and several enthusiastic people were giving a grotesque turn from their own and their neighbors’ calamities by terrible predictions. Even then, however, my mother and I, notwithstanding the danger that passed and which still threatened us, had no thoughts of leaving the place till we should receive some tidings of my uncle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And now, you will read this narrative, so far beneath the dignity of a history, without any view of transferring it to your own; and indeed you must attribute it to your own request, if it appears scarcely worthy of a letter. Farewell.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnotes&#34;&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:1&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pliny, the Younger, &lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://ryanfb.xyz/loebolus-data/L055.pdf&#34;&gt;Letters&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/i&gt;, trans. W. Melmoth, ed. W. M. L. Hutchinson, Loeb Classical Library (Macmillan, 1915).&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:2&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Plin. &lt;i xml:lang=&#34;la&#34;&gt;Ep.&lt;/i&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.perseus.tufts.edu/hopper/text?doc=urn:cts:latinLit:phi1318.phi001.perseus-lat1:6.16&#34;&gt;6.16&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.perseus.tufts.edu/hopper/text?doc=urn:cts:latinLit:phi1318.phi001.perseus-lat1:6.20&#34;&gt;6.20&lt;/a&gt;. (G. Crane, Ed.) Perseus Digital Library.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:3&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;August 24th. Believed to be a mistake in the manuscript. &amp;ldquo;Despite the date of August 24th is widely accepted in the literature&amp;hellip; the most probable date must necessarily fall between October 24th and November 1st.&amp;rdquo; Doronzom M, &lt;i xml:lang=&#34;la&#34;&gt;et al.&lt;/i&gt; &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1016/j.earscirev.2022.104072&#34;&gt;The 79 CE eruption of Vesuvius&lt;/a&gt;.&amp;rdquo; &lt;i&gt;Earth-Science Reviews&lt;/i&gt;, 2022:104072.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:4&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A quotation from Virgil, &lt;a href=&#34;https://ryanfb.xyz/loebolus-data/L063N.pdf#page=312&#34;&gt;&lt;i xml:lang=&#34;la&#34;&gt;Aeneid&lt;/i&gt; 2.12&lt;/a&gt;.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:4&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
	</item>
	
	<item>
		<title>Diglossic, parallel CSS</title>
		<link>https://ettedh.github.io/articles/diglossic-text/</link>
		<pubDate>Sat, 22 Mar 2025 08:28:28 -0500</pubDate>
		
		<guid>https://ettedh.github.io/articles/diglossic-text/</guid>
		<description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;diglossic-text.css&lt;/code&gt; (&lt;a href=&#34;https://ettedh.github.io/diglossic-text.css&#34;&gt;link to the stylesheet&lt;/a&gt;) is a stylesheet to help create diglossic texts with properly-flowing, progressive, &lt;em&gt;correct&lt;/em&gt;, HTML. Its features include:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;aligning like elements in columns,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;selectable, single-source texts,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;unobstructed by HTML-isms like &lt;code&gt;div&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;table&lt;/code&gt;,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;being readable, even without CSS (for future-proofing).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have a &lt;a href=&#34;https://ettedh.github.io/mul/texts/famo/&#34;&gt;demo set up&lt;/a&gt; on my website. Here is what it looks like:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;diglossic-text&#34;&gt;
&lt;!-- --&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;diglossic-l&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;first-text&#34;&gt;First text&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lorem ipsum dolor sit amet&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- --&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;diglossic-r&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;second-text&#34;&gt;Second text&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pain itself desires pain&amp;hellip;&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is supported by all modern desktop web browsers (Chrome, Firefox&lt;code&gt;++&lt;/code&gt;). To use the file, add the following line to your document head:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34; style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-html&#34; data-lang=&#34;html&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;link&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#a6e22e&#34;&gt;href&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;/diglossic-text.css&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#a6e22e&#34;&gt;rel&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;stylesheet&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;&amp;gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;Then, format your text (assuming a &lt;a href=&#34;https://daringfireball.net/projects/markdown/&#34;&gt;Markdown&lt;/a&gt; format) like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34; style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-html&#34; data-lang=&#34;html&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;This paragraph will not be rendered in two columns.
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;div&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#a6e22e&#34;&gt;class&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;diglossic-text&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;&amp;gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#75715e&#34;&gt;&amp;lt;!-- --&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;span&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#a6e22e&#34;&gt;class&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;diglossic-l&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;span&lt;/span&gt;&amp;gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;### First text
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;Lorem ipsum dolor sit amet...
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#75715e&#34;&gt;&amp;lt;!-- --&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;span&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#a6e22e&#34;&gt;class&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#e6db74&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;diglossic-r&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;span&lt;/span&gt;&amp;gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;### Second text
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;Pain itself desires pain...
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;lt;/&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;div&lt;/span&gt;&amp;gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;This text is outside of the diglossic text.
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;Keep in mind that only the block-level elements of &lt;code&gt;h1--h6&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;p&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;blockquote&lt;/code&gt;, and &lt;code&gt;pre&lt;/code&gt; are rendered in parallel. All parallel texts must have the same number of blocks to line up properly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;why-make-this&#34;&gt;Why make this?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.hup.harvard.edu/series/loeb-classical-library&#34;&gt;Loeb Classical Library&lt;/a&gt; is a beautiful series of Latin and Greek texts, with English translations, published by Harvard University Press.  Their books feature the source text on the left page, with the translation on the right page.  It seems like all other implementations fall short on at least one of my goals, as well as &lt;a href=&#34;https://motherfuckingwebsite.com&#34;&gt;working on the web&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnotes&#34;&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:1&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The horizontal lines are not part of the formatting, just something to make it clear what is what.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
	</item>
	
	<item>
		<title>Camino Real</title>
		<link>https://ettedh.github.io/texts/camino-real/</link>
		<pubDate>Fri, 14 Mar 2025 17:30:33 -0500</pubDate>
		
		<guid>https://ettedh.github.io/texts/camino-real/</guid>
		<description>&lt;p&gt;I scramble gleefully up a concrete incline six feet above the cobblestone road, but Hal Jackson saunters. We stand in the ruins of what was once a large house, twenty minutes outside Zacatecas, Mexico. The air is cool. Scrubby mountains pocked with old silver mines sweep across the landscape. Jackson is uneasy. I collect several pebbles, fallen pieces of wall. Jackson shakes his head, wanders the brush. &amp;ldquo;This is disappointing,&amp;rdquo; he says, eyes scanning, GPS in one hand, notepad in the other, camera slung round his neck. &lt;i&gt;Why?&lt;/i&gt; &amp;ldquo;It just seems&amp;hellip;&amp;rdquo; he trails off, gingerly steps over a sharp rock embedded in the earth. He was once a marathoner, and though it&amp;rsquo;s been thirteen years since his last, he maintains a runner&amp;rsquo;s lean grace. At seventy he looks perhaps fifty-five. &amp;ldquo;I thought it&amp;rsquo;d be bigger,&amp;rdquo; he mutters. &amp;ldquo;This doesn&amp;rsquo;t seem right.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are in Pánuco, the birthplace of Juan de Oñate, the last of the Spanish conquistadors, whose hand likely had more influence on the American Southwest and northern Mexico than that of any other single explorer. In 1598, Oñate blazed the &lt;i xml:lang=&#34;es&#34;&gt;Camino Real de Tierra Adentro&lt;/i&gt;, a trail that became the most used and most significant route of commerce and culture for three hundred years. At its peak the Camino Real ran 1,800 miles from Mexico City north to Santa Fe. Spaniards used the trail to settle towns and villages all along the way, Franciscans used it to spread their gospel, troops from the United States and Mexico used it for waging battles and building forts, Indians used it to fight the swelling tide of foreigners, and traders used it for commerce. All morning, Jackson and I have searched for the remains of the Oñate family hacienda, and now, with the Jeep Cherokee parked conspicuously on the narrow road, clouds in full bloom beyond the mountains, and my pocket full of pebbles, Jackson&amp;rsquo;s doubt continues to deepen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A man in stained white jeans and a thinning white undershirt wanders down the road below us in sandals. He greets the two gringos standing atop a ruined wall in a pool of packed dirt bursting with purple wildflowers. Jackson tells him we want Oñate&amp;rsquo;s villa; the man looks bemused, then beckons us down from our perch.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A quarter mile up and three minutes later we find the hacienda for real: an enormous hillock of pink cobblestones with a wall running around the circumference, a turret in the middle, the remnants of an ancient pool, a burrowed garden. The place is grand and empty. Silent with a cool breeze. It bears not a single marker indicating what it once was or who lived here. We three wander about it. Now Jackson is gleeful, running to take pictures, climbing up on the walls to peer at the vistas, his dusty white baseball hat nearly flying off behind him. &amp;ldquo;Now this⁠—&amp;rdquo; he grins, index finger poised in the air⁠—“this is what I pictured.  &lt;em&gt;This&amp;hellip;is&amp;hellip;it!&lt;/em&gt;”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Throughout New Mexico and Texas, Oñate&amp;rsquo;s trail is clearly marked, but in Mexico many parts of it remained unknown to modern explorers, and Jackson and I set out on a mission to find them. We carried minutely detailed topographical maps and aerial maps from the early twentieth century, which often showed a trail obvious from a bird&amp;rsquo;s-eye view but elusive on the ground. We also carried copies of travelers&amp;rsquo; journals that contained specific descriptions of the natural landscape, of mountains and valleys that wouldn&amp;rsquo;t have changed much, and of rest areas for caravans that still bore names Oñate had given them. Thus we had a decent idea of where things should have been if they hadn&amp;rsquo;t been paved or farmed over. &amp;ldquo;Trail finding,&amp;rdquo; Jackson assured me, &amp;ldquo;can be an exact science.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Certain facts held true about the trail regardless of any particular location. For example, it always ran above the flood-plain. Also, water was a constant concern, so the caravans went for a route where it was accessible and where attacks by hostile Apache or Comanche Indians came infrequently. &lt;i xml:lang=&#34;es&#34;&gt;Acequias&lt;/i&gt;⁠—irrigation ditches⁠—often paralleled the trail, and they do even today in pueblos and small towns where they are still used. Oñate&amp;rsquo;s hacienda marked the final discovery of our journey, and the apex above all the others. Without Oñate, the trail might never have existed. Without Oñate, geographical boundaries, language, culture, battles, history, food, family, ethnic and racial intersection, economics, trade, and travel would have been vastly different. Without Oñate, Jackson and I⁠—a generation and 1,500 miles apart from each other⁠—would have never met four hundred years later.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our fortuitous guide explained what each walled section might have represented in Oñate&amp;rsquo;s day. He showed us how to climb over trees, and through holes in the walls where vegetation had overgrown the pathways; he pointed out where the aqueduct ran in from the mountains. Hal took measurements, notes, and pictures; he clicked his GPS. We climbed halfway up a mountain for an eagle&amp;rsquo;s-eye view. Were this hacienda in the United States, historical preservation societies would have tagged, ticketed, and renovated it; it would not be inhabited by local fauna and ignored by humans. This was the home of a man who changed the course of history. For Jackson and me, it marked the end of a long journey, but for Juan de Oñate and his Camino Real, this place was just the beginning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Built originally by the Spanish Empire to connect capital cities to one another, &lt;i xml:lang=&#34;es&#34;&gt;camino reals&lt;/i&gt;, or royal roads, snaked throughout what is now the Western United States and Mexico. But there is only one &lt;i xml:lang=&#34;es&#34;&gt;Camino Real de Tierra Adentro&lt;/i&gt;, the one Jackson and I drove; in addition to its incredible length, it predates the other &lt;i xml:lang=&#34;es&#34;&gt;camino reals&lt;/i&gt; by more than two hundred years, according to George Torok, president of the Camino Real de Tierra Adentro (CARTA) association.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Beyond simply offering a way to get around, the Camino Real became a palimpsest of cultural, religious, economic, and ethnic crossovers.  Skirmishes, business deals, wars, and treaties were wrought along its path. Like the old Route 66 of the United States, it was as much a cultural symbol as a practical method of travel. Unlike America&amp;rsquo;s modern day expressways, which mostly skirt cities and often divide ethnicities and races from one neighborhood to the next, Oñate&amp;rsquo;s Camino Real, our country&amp;rsquo;s first superhighway, brought states, countries, and people together.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because of it, Indians went from &amp;ldquo;hunting grubs to being warriors of the Plains in a single generation after the introduction of the horse,&amp;rdquo; Jackson says; he calls the animal a &amp;ldquo;technological revolution.&amp;rdquo; Mission churches replaced &lt;i xml:lang=&#34;hop&#34;&gt;kivas&lt;/i&gt; as community centers, and villages began to gather around central squares. Catholicism flourished. Crops like corn, beans, and squash were introduced. The English and Spanish tongues mingled and eventually overwhelmed pueblo languages. Even food preparation changed, as the Spaniards taught Mexican Indians the concept of frying. Chickens, pigs, sheep, and goats arrived, along with new forms of architecture, new diseases, and new kinds of enslavement by the Spaniards. &amp;ldquo;There is constant traffic where the trail went up from Mexico,&amp;rdquo; Torok told me. &amp;ldquo;It&amp;rsquo;s still happening today: the migration, the immigration, the influence. It wasn&amp;rsquo;t a finite time period.&amp;rdquo; The Camino Real grew into a cultural system inscribed on the land itself. As we move forward in the present, it seems to say, we are bound to the past.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Its history can be loosely divided into six periods: 1598⁠–⁠1680, when Oñate and his successors connected the paths that led from village to village into what we recognize as the Camino Real today; 1680⁠–⁠93, when the Pueblo Indians revolted against the invasion of their culture and expelled the Spaniards from northern territories for thirteen years; 1693⁠–⁠1821, with the Spaniards back again and the Camino Real once more a thoroughfare for commerce, culture, and war; 1821⁠–⁠80, when Mexico gained its independence and Americans were allowed to trade; followed by the Mexican War of 1846⁠–⁠48, which made the northern stretch of the &lt;i xml:lang=&#34;es&#34;&gt;Camino Real&lt;/i&gt; American; and finally, the 1880s when the rails replaced the road. A few paved parts of the Camino Real are still used unchanged today in pueblos and small towns, but for a purist like Jackson, the trail&amp;rsquo;s great days are gone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jackson and I began our tour in early July, just about the worst time to do a lot of driving through the desert. Having retired as a professor from Humblodt State University, Jackson now spends his days on the trail. He serves as president of the Santa Fe Trail Association, and he wrote the revised version of Marc Simmons&amp;rsquo;s &lt;i&gt;Following the Santa Fe Trail: A Guide for Modern Travelers&lt;/i&gt;.&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Last May, he helped form the Camino Real Trail Association, and he&amp;rsquo;s now writing a guidebook about that trail, to be published this June by the University of New Mexico Press. He has been a political geographer, and he wrote his dissertation on a squatters&amp;rsquo; village outside Mexico City, so his idea of place is inextricably linked to people and policy. He&amp;rsquo;s a diehard liberal, but his biggest complaint about archeologists, anthropologists, and sociologists⁠—all of whose subjects overlap with cultural geography⁠—is that they just don&amp;rsquo;t make good maps.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To say that Jackson is a map man is like saying that astronauts enjoy air travel. He doesn&amp;rsquo;t just &lt;em&gt;like&lt;/em&gt; maps; he lives by them. He keeps topographical and aerial maps organized by route in a box in the back seat of his car, next to atlases, road maps, Lonely Planet maps, and historical maps. In his home office, he has maps framed on the walls, maps in filing cabinets, and maps laid out over his desk. Each morning after breakfast, maps cover his dining room table. He has computer programs to make maps. At various points during our journey, he offered to make me maps including or excluding such features as power lines, bodies of water, villages, and mountains. He doesn&amp;rsquo;t like to be lost. He told me once that he figured he looked at maps a hundred times a day.  &amp;ldquo;I&amp;rsquo;m the where guy,&amp;rdquo; he says. He respects maps, and they in turn have given him the assurance of one who always knows his place in the world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our route began north of Santa Fe in the San Juan Pueblo, which Oñate occupied in July of 1598. Large excavations have been done in this area, so the location of the original mission church and central square are denoted by a marker, in the midst of a field of chamise and juniper beside a graveyard. &amp;ldquo;In northern New Mexico, there&amp;rsquo;s still a lot of resentment today toward Oñate, whose soldiers were said to be savage,&amp;rdquo; Jackson said. He illustrated this with a story about the Acoma Pueblo just outside Albuquerque. The tale claims that the Indians were living peacefully when Oñate&amp;rsquo;s men descended on them, and chopped off the right foot of every man over sixteen. As the Spanish tell it, the Acomas attacked the Spaniards first, and the latter were merely retaliating. Several years ago, on the eve of the opening of a new Oñate museum, north of the San Juan Pueblo along the road to Taos, someone chopped off the right foot of Oñate&amp;rsquo;s statue.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With close to five hundred people following him, Oñate, whose soldiers often marched in full body armor through the desert heat, averaged fifteen miles a day. Jackson and I covered fifteen times that. Remarkably, Oñate managed to establish the first American thoroughfare, predating the colony of Jamestown, yet has never received much historical credit. The author Marc Simmons, who wrote of Oñate&amp;rsquo;s perilous journey in &lt;em&gt;The Last Conquistador&lt;/em&gt;, said that along with everything else the conquistador did to establish the shape and character of North America, he also &amp;ldquo;made a notable contribution, through his wide-ranging explorations, toward an understanding of the true geography of western America.&amp;rdquo;&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:2&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just ten miles outside Santa Fe, Jackson showed me my first swale, a carved-out bowl of earth, where deep cuts from wagon wheels could still be detected. &amp;ldquo;I get excited about swales,&amp;rdquo; he told me, &amp;ldquo;but not everyone does. Standing where something happened is very powerful to me.&amp;rdquo; In the distance La Majada Mesa loomed black and foreboding. In Oñate&amp;rsquo;s time, the mesa was a near-insurmountable challenge to cross. Wagons had to be emptied, and their goods carried steeply uphill on horseback while the carts were routed through the shallow river that cleaved the mesa.  Loaded with their cargoes, the carts would have been mired in the riverbed. In &lt;em&gt;Commerce of the Prairies&lt;/em&gt;, perhaps the best traveler&amp;rsquo;s account of the Camino Real, Josiah Gregg, a mid-nineteenth-century trader, wrote of the treacherous crossings: &amp;ldquo;In some places, if a wagon is permitted to stop in the river but for a moment, it sinks to the very body &lt;i xml:lang=&#34;la&#34;&gt;[sic]&lt;/i&gt;. Instances have occurred when it became necessary, not only to drag out the mules by the ears and to carry out the loading package by package, but to haul out the wagon piece by piece⁠—wheel by wheel.&amp;rdquo;&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:3&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We drove to the base of La Majada Mesa, parked in the dust, and got out to walk along the old trail. &amp;ldquo;Look at this.&amp;rdquo; Jackson shook his head, pointed to where the trail had created an obvious swale, then disappeared from view ’round the bend of the mountain. Jackson believed few people even noticed the mountain. &amp;ldquo;Ten miles outside Santa Fe and not a single footprint,&amp;rdquo; he said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As we drove, the terracotta countryside gave way to rich, red clay hills and low cliffs, and I began to learn how to read a landscape.  Jackson pointed out that curved roads in a grid city, for example, were very likely just old trails paved over. The entire city of Boston is the most famous example of this. Parts of the Camino Real that are paved prove the fact. &amp;ldquo;The caravans took the best route, not necessarily north, east, south, and west,&amp;rdquo; Jackson told me, as we drove trail areas near his home in Placitas, New Mexico, just outside Albuquerque. &amp;ldquo;A crooked street in a city laid out by &lt;i xml:lang=&#34;es&#34;&gt;gringos&lt;/i&gt;?  You can be sure it predates the grid.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a flat plain, carved-out swales often collected rainwater and runoff, so a long row of green bushes in a mostly barren landscape might mean the trail had run through there. Or a straight cut through a lush green area might signal the trail&amp;rsquo;s presence. Jackson was a landscape detective alert for clues. An oddly shaped mountain had been mined; a mound of dirt was a melted adobe house; a shallow gully, an ancient trail. In nature, context is everything. We scanned the land for the easiest route, the most level, and then we looked for angles. Where north⁠–⁠south paved roads ran, the Camino Real often bisected them today at 45-degree angles. We spent a lot of time in the Jeep slowing down, reversing, advancing, retracing our path. At one point, south of Socorro, Jackson remarked that the oxen from trail-day caravans ate beans off the mesquite tree, and the beans left behind in the cattle&amp;rsquo;s droppings eventually grew into trees, so there were areas where long, straight rows of mesquite trees amid otherwise random vegetation were obvious clues to the Camino Real.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Later we drove to San Pedro, a ghost town in New Mexico and once a stop along the trail, where a field of long-abandoned adobe houses has slowly dissolved during years of rain, sun, and neglect. One small ravine, once surely an acequia, was now host to tangles of weeds, paddle cactus, and thornbushes that crackled under my hiking boots. In the far distance Jackson and I heard voices coming from several trailers, followed by two distinctive pops of a shotgun. &amp;ldquo;Guess we&amp;rsquo;d better not linger,&amp;rdquo; he said, making his way slowly back toward the car. I was reluctant to leave.  There are places on the trail today still populated, some large, some small, but none that I had seen like San Pedro, whose ravaged buildings so powerfully suggested the sad place between existing and forgotten.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From New Mexico, Jackson and I made our way south toward Mexico, via the infamous &lt;i xml:lang=&#34;es&#34;&gt;Jornada del Muerto&lt;/i&gt;⁠—in English, the Journey of the Dead Man.  Christened after Oñate&amp;rsquo;s day, it maintains the name still. A ninety-mile swatch of desolation between Socorro and Las Cruces, this was one of three long &lt;i xml:lang=&#34;es&#34;&gt;jornadas&lt;/i&gt; through enormous chunks of desert. The flat, sandy plain was punctuated by paddle cactus and what Jackson called, in geographer&amp;rsquo;s parlance, &amp;ldquo;desert pavement”⁠—rocks blown by the wind off nearby mountains. Caravans often left after 4:00 p.m. and traveled through the night to avoid the jornada&amp;rsquo;s relentless sun. Water was a constant worry, and travelers&amp;rsquo; journals again and again described the white bones of man and beast littering the landscape. Even I, a modern traveler with all the conveniences, did not escape the jornada, when I pulled out a blood-tipped mesquite thorn that had gone through the sole of my shoe and lodged in my foot. Gregg&amp;rsquo;s section of the Jornada del Muerto told of the luck his party had had in not losing a single person during the crossing. &amp;ldquo;One thing appears very certain,&amp;rdquo; he wrote, &amp;ldquo;that this dangerous pass has cost the life of many travelers in days of yore⁠&amp;hellip; we felt truly grateful that the arid Jornada had not been productive of more serious consequences to our party.&amp;rdquo; &lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:4&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:4&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In El Paso we met up with CARTA&amp;rsquo;s president, George Torok, and Ben Brown, an archeologist employed by Mexico&amp;rsquo;s National Institute of Anthropology and History (&lt;i xml:lang=&#34;es&#34;&gt;Instituto Nacionale de Antropologia e Historia&lt;/i&gt;), whose work has led him to study various areas around or on the Camino Real. Brown and Torok showed us around several border areas where the Spaniards took up residence after their expulsion in 1680 during the Pueblo revolt.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We drove first through pecan groves and cornfields, to Ciudad Juárez, the Mexican urban extension of El Paso and, after the Pueblo revolt, the northernmost boundary of the Spanish territory. Two Camino Real routes led south from Juárez. One, through sand dunes, has horrific accounts of carcasses in the sand like those in the jornada; the second was less direct but easier. Next to Juárez&amp;rsquo;s enormous cathedral in the central square stands the original whitewashed mission church built in 1659 and the oldest mission along the trail still functioning. In the square this day, preachers shouted Protestant theology into crackling loudspeakers, and pigeons commanded the immediate airspace. Just south of the mission a three-story covered market sat where the central market had stood during trail days, when it marked an important resupply spot famous for El Paso&amp;rsquo;s wines, brandy, and fruit. Then it was the only place between the Mexican city of Chihuahua and Santa Fe, New Mexico, where lush green vegetation flourished, a fact no longer true in modern-day Juárez, with its increasingly short water supply. &amp;ldquo;The Camino Real is really a communication trail,&amp;rdquo; Ben Brown told me. &amp;ldquo;Its social impact was with knowledge and items going north and south. It&amp;rsquo;s not just a trail in the physical sense; it&amp;rsquo;s really a concept of communication.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We drove through various settlements where the Spanish retreated after the 1680 revolt. Ysleta del Sur, Senecú, San Elizario, San Lorenzo, and Socorro del Sur all were small communities and are laid out today as they were in trail days, with a mission-style church, a central square, and a small but growing sense of their place in history. At these settlements, Torok told me, the names had changed, the Camino Real path had changed, the river had changed, and the people and the culture had continually changed. The Rio Grande, which is the established border between the United States and Mexico, constantly shifts its location.  The earth is not silent, not static, even if we wish our boundaries to be so. The river is far south of where it was in Oñate&amp;rsquo;s day and, as a result, makes for a rather odd choice for an international boundary line.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a little town called Bracito, which was a resting stop along the trail in the eighteenth and nineteenth centuries, a small but significant battle took place during the Mexican War of 1846⁠–⁠48, right in front of today&amp;rsquo;s Bracito School. Brown and Jackson stood at the mouth of an acequia, respectfully debating the trail&amp;rsquo;s location (Brown: underneath the acequia; Jackson: alongside it), and why the Americans who were outnumbered three-to-one by the Mexicans won the battle in twenty minutes (Brown: Mexicans were an ill-treated peasant army with low morale; Jackson: Americans were Missouri volunteers well used to their weaponry). As they talked, each with one leg resting atop the modern concrete wall of the old acequia, the sun began to set, lighting up the school. Lightning shot down from the clouds in the distance, and sheets of rain rolled in. Whether the Camino Real ran below or adjacent to the acequia, today a railroad track crosses where we all stood discussing what happened here once, watching as the storm and nightfall came on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Mexico, Jackson and I were alone again, searching for the first of many areas we hoped to find that had eluded modern day explorers, including Ojo de Lucero, a spring that nearly every journal mentioned that had watered a rest stop from Oñate&amp;rsquo;s day. In the Mexican state of Chihuahua, Jackson scanned the placid golden landscape, and I felt the Jeep slow. He pulled the car off the highway onto a two-track dust road in the middle of the desert. I hadn&amp;rsquo;t even seen the two-track, let alone whatever infinitesimal clue between this swatch of desert and the last had made him turn off for closer inspection. To Jackson, each new vista of desert offered a slightly altered landscape, a tiny promise of discovery. The Lucero spring would have once held enough water for a thousand people or more to drink, wash, and cook from for a few days in a trailside camp, but today it would be only an enormous indentation in the earth. If we found Lucero, we would be among just a handful of people in the world who knew where it was now, and who knew that it once meant, for many thousands of people, survival.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jackson drove a mile off the highway on the two-track until we reached a private ranch in the midst of new construction. A man in a construction hat walked briskly to our car and peered in suspiciously. Jackson waved a greeting, rolling down his window. The man told us that what we wanted was across the highway. &amp;ldquo;&lt;i xml:lang=&#34;es&#34;&gt;No aqui&lt;/i&gt;,&amp;rdquo; he said several times in a voice meant to warn us away from our folly. Jackson gunned the engine, backed up, and retraced our route to the highway, at which point he grumbled, &amp;ldquo;He doesn&amp;rsquo;t know what the hell we&amp;rsquo;re looking for.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moments later he spotted a flash of aqua blue up ahead. &amp;ldquo;Aha,&amp;rdquo; he said enigmatically. Jackson read the landscape as an artist reads a blank canvas, wrought with possibility and inherently full of layers and details that the rest of us nonartists could not imagine. The blue dot became clearer as we drove, and I saw that it was an &lt;i xml:lang=&#34;es&#34;&gt;alberca&lt;/i&gt;, a public swimming pool. Jackson conversed with the alberca&amp;rsquo;s maintenance man, and he pointed in the direction we had come from. Afterward Jackson turned to me rather as a superhero might to his faithful but somewhat ineffectual sidekick and said, &amp;ldquo;Let&amp;rsquo;s get the maps!&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ten minutes later, Jeep parked askew amid mesquite trees and choya cactus with pipe-cleaner arms, we stood at Ojo de Lucero. We&amp;rsquo;d driven along a two-track past scattered ranches, then turned into the desert until the trees got too thick to drive, and then we walked, carrying bundles of papers, maps, and Jackson&amp;rsquo;s digital GPS. Several hundred yards away was a tiny village, so Jackson knew there was a water source from somewhere. We noted nearby power lines, which showed up on the topo maps, and after a brief tromp through the desert, we stood at a shallow dry indentation in the earth, a small pipe pumping water through the desert.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The finding, though, was remarkably anticlimactic. Jackson marked the spot in his GPS device, then grinned for a moment until his mind jumped to what we had yet to find. In the world of Hal Jackson, if something hadn&amp;rsquo;t been found in four hundred-or-so years, it wasn&amp;rsquo;t so much a matter of its concealment as that no one had ever really bothered to look. Lucero was an auspicious sign of things to come.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We drove on through the Mexican desert. At Carrizal we stopped at what had once been a presidio. The walls had dwindled to a rectangular speed bump in the earth. In the late eighteenth and early nineteenth centuries, Spaniards bribed Apaches with food to ward off thievery in what was likely the first real attempt at social welfare. Later, in 1916, Americans⁠—mostly Buffalo Soldiers⁠—lost a small battle to Mexicans here. In the distance, dust devils flitted across faraway plains. &lt;i&gt;You could watch your dog run away for days in land like this&lt;/i&gt;, I told Jackson, a phrase often said of the Midwest, where I happened to live. Jackson laughed, then, grew thoughtful. Every place you ever go will be compared with where you came from: the weather, the architecture, the context. &amp;ldquo;You never escape your own landscape,&amp;rdquo; he said. &amp;ldquo;It&amp;rsquo;s like gum on your shoe.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Later we searched for another &lt;i xml:lang=&#34;es&#34;&gt;ojo&lt;/i&gt;: Caliente. Like Lucero, it was mentioned in every journal; unlike Lucero, Jackson didn&amp;rsquo;t know of many people who had ever managed to locate it. Using topo maps, we pulled off the highway onto a two-track and searched through the flat-planed dust for a road shown on the map. We drove up, looked, reversed, drove back up, looked again, and reversed, over and over. Between the irrigated alfalfa fields, the russet land managed only an occasional barrel cactus. Suddenly, a migrant worker appeared at the window of our Jeep.  After the man gave us directions, Jackson and I easily spotted the tiny road that had eluded us. We lifted a metal-wire gate off its wooden hinge and drove in till we had to hoof it through the mesquite. Two things appeared in front of us: an enormous ocher-and-bronze-colored church⁠—too new to be Caliente⁠—and a lone brown cow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We split up and searched through the trees, more animals appearing as we wandered: horses, cows, quail, a blackeared jackrabbit. Suddenly, in the distance, I heard Jackson hollering. He was buried deep in the trees, so I followed his voice and saw first the old church. It was just as Gregg&amp;rsquo;s journal and so many others had said: graveyard next to the church, &lt;i xml:lang=&#34;es&#34;&gt;padre&lt;/i&gt;&amp;rsquo;s home opposite. If this was really Ojo de Caliente, we could expect an enormous ojo and the Camino Real trail leading smack-dab into the church.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I found Jackson standing in the middle of the hole. It was dried up now, probably forty-by-twenty feet, but huge trees around its circumference suggested that water abounded deep down. Jackson was downright giddy.  Around the ojo and church were mounds that had once been adobe houses.  &amp;ldquo;It&amp;rsquo;s probable that no modern explorer has ever been here,&amp;rdquo; he said.  &amp;ldquo;And certainly no settlement for ninety or so years.&amp;rdquo; He jog-walked from end to end in the ojo, measured the whole thing, and took a GPS position.  Lizards darted across the ground. We felt as if we had been granted the memory of every traveler who ever walked that land. We ran atop and through the ojo, took pictures in the padre&amp;rsquo;s quarters, padded over the mounds where houses once stood. Then we wandered around to the back of the church, and there it was, clear as day: a single straight brown swale surrounded on both sides by overgrown mesquite trees. The Camino Real, with all but street signs pointing it out. Our elation was so great we simply stared, overwhelmed, silenced.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We found other things: the route of the trail in a charming, colorful village called Valle de Allende, where the air was cool, the trees were voluminous, and the town smelled of wet earth and roasted chilies. Oñate and his minions had crossed a stream there. We drove on past rolling green hills, out of the desert and into a land of eucalyptus and pine, to a town called Villa Hidalgo today and Cerro Gordo back in the trail days. We found the makings of an old presidio wall possibly from those trail days.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On a side road made of what appeared to be a scattering of stones embedded at random in the dirt, Jackson peered so close for so long that a pattern emerged. &amp;ldquo;Here,&amp;rdquo; he told me, &amp;ldquo;a straight line of rocks. You see that? That&amp;rsquo;s not accidental.&amp;rdquo; He got so excited he had to take a breath. &amp;ldquo;That was put there by someone. &lt;em&gt;On purpose&lt;/em&gt;.&amp;rdquo; A moment later an old Indian couple walked out of a nearby doorway and greeted us. Jackson pointed to the rocks. &lt;i xml:lang=&#34;es&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;Camino Real, aqui?&amp;rdquo; &lt;/i&gt; he asked. The woman shrugged and invited us into her home, where her husband, in peasant hat and beat-up jeans, confirmed that indeed his home was on the trail. The rocks, he told us, were the old method of paving. We sat then and talked with them about what we were doing: a fusion of generations, cultures, and languages, exploring a history of generations, cultures, and languages.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That night a band of musicians walked through the streets of Zacatecas, Mexico, where Oñate&amp;rsquo;s family was once famous for its silver mines. There are still Oñates there today, and the pink-stoned buildings of Zacatecas are still surrounded by mines whose silver is coveted the world over.  Tomorrow we would head to Oñate&amp;rsquo;s birthplace, Pánuco, and search for the spot where everything started, but tonight we would celebrate. As the band marched, people in the streets followed until the crowd was more than a block long. Car horns wailed as the entourage passed. Jackson and I were swept up with the throng, hurrying along the cobblestones behind the band. On the sidewalks, people danced, and the band stopped and played for several couples. A Mexican man in a white shirt pulled me by the hand and swung me around to the music. I laughed, and Jackson snapped a picture, and then the skies opened, and raindrops the size of pebbles crashed over our heads and all around us. But the band played on, and I kept dancing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnotes&#34;&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:1&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Marc Simmons, H. Jackson, &lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://lccn.loc.gov/00064568&#34;&gt;Following the Santa Fe Trail: a Guide for Modern Travelers&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/i&gt; (Santa Fe: Ancient City Press, 2001).&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:2&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Marc Simmons, &lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://lccn.loc.gov/90050697&#34;&gt;The Last Conquistador: Juan de Oñate and the settling of the far Southwest&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/i&gt; (Univ. Oklahoma Press, 1991).&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:3&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Josiah Gregg, &lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://hdl.handle.net/2027/mdp.39015008586714?urlappend=%3Bseq=288&#34;&gt;The Commerce of the Prairies&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/i&gt; (Lakeside Press, 1926), 242&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:4&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gregg, &lt;a href=&#34;https://hdl.handle.net/2027/mdp.39015008586714?urlappend=%3Bseq=286&#34;&gt;240&lt;/a&gt;.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:4&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
	</item>
	
	<item>
		<title>Chicago’s Natural Divisions and Plant Communities</title>
		<link>https://ettedh.github.io/texts/plants-chicago-region/</link>
		<pubDate>Wed, 27 Nov 2024 10:14:31 -0600</pubDate>
		
		<guid>https://ettedh.github.io/texts/plants-chicago-region/</guid>
		<description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;natural-divisions-of-the-chicago-region&#34;&gt;Natural Divisions of the Chicago Region&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The authors are indebted to Kenneth Mierzwa of TAMS Consultants, Inc., Chicago, Ill., for having made available for this book a synopsis of the Natural Divisions of the Chicago Region, a distillation of a forthcoming paper.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Homoya &lt;em&gt;et al.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; describe a natural division as a &amp;ldquo;generalized unit of the landscape where a distinctive assemblage of natural features is present.&amp;rdquo; Natural divisions maps are a synthesis of geology, physiography, soils, hydrology, presettlement vegetation, and characteristic fauna. They soon will be available for all four of the states included within the Chicago region.&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref1:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:2&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:3&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:4&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:4&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:5&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:5&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; The current effort combines maps of the four states and adds additional detail that reflects the regional scale. For example, the Morainal Section in Illinois&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref1:2&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; and the Valparaiso Moraine Section in Indiana&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref2:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; are valid concepts when viewed within the context of each state, but when this section is extended along the Valparaiso and associated moraines from Wisconsin to Michigan, it must be split at some point. The beech-maple forests of our eastern section are too distinct from the oak savannas and prairies of our western section to be included in the same unit. Similarly, the lake plain is elevated to division status, and subdivided to reflect significant differences among the black-soil prairies once present on the site of modern-day Chicago, the sand savannas of much of the northwestern Indiana lake plain, and the more heavily wooded lake plain of Michigan and adjacent Indiana. These new boundaries address the east to west transition from forest to prairie.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
    &lt;img src=&#34;https://ettedh.github.io/pics/cdiv.webp&#34; alt=&#34;Map of counties 75 miles around Chicago. The map outlines the natural divisions in bold lines, with subdivisions in smaller lines.&#34;&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Natural divisions of the Chicago Region&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;morainal-natural-division&#34;&gt;Morainal Natural Division&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Young and rolling morainal topography close to Lake Michigan. The boundary follows the outer edge of the Valparaiso Moraine except in the northwest, where the line is based on geological features and presettlement vegetation.&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref2:2&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;1a-western-morainal-section&#34;&gt;1A. Western Morainal Section&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mostly end moraines. Soils with a high clay content and often a perched water table. Primarily prairie and savanna, with isolated areas of mesic woodland and forest.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;1b-eastern-morainal-section&#34;&gt;1B. Eastern Morainal Section&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Eastern portion of the Valparaiso Morainal system. Geologically similar to &lt;a href=&#34;https://ettedh.github.io/texts/plants-chicago-region/#1a-western-morainal-section&#34;&gt;1A&lt;/a&gt;, but a break is made based on the predominant plant communities. Mostly timbered with savannas and forests.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;1c-kettle-moraine-section&#34;&gt;1C. Kettle Moraine Section&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Characterized by truncated end moraines, outwash features, kame and kettle topography, an unconsolidated aquifer, and glacial lakes. Savannas were once the principal plant community, interspersed with prairies, sedge meadows, fens, small spring-fed streams, and marshes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;1d-racine-till-plain-section&#34;&gt;1D. Racine Till Plain Section&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mostly end and ground moraines; timbered principally with mesic savanna or forest. Ravines along Lake Michigan include a number of boreal relict plants.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;1e-winnebago-drift-section&#34;&gt;1E. Winnebago Drift Section&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Altonian substage of the Wisconsinan glaciation, earlier than other sections of the Morainal Natural Division. Topography somewhat more level and wetlands less common; streams more entrenched and drainage patterns better developed. Savannas and dry prairies predominated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;1f-fox-river-bluff-section&#34;&gt;1F. Fox River Bluff Section&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Characterized by moderately high bluffs along the lower Fox River Valley, and associated outwash features and dolomite outcrops. Seepage areas and fens occur along the bluffs. Included within the Morainal Division because of the fens similar to those in &lt;a href=&#34;https://ettedh.github.io/texts/plants-chicago-region/#1c-kettle-moraine-section&#34;&gt;1C&lt;/a&gt;, and extensive woodlands associated with the bluffs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;lake-plain-natural-division&#34;&gt;Lake Plain Natural Division&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Characterized by lacustrine deposits and aeolian dunes. Included within the Morainal Division by previous authors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;2a-chicago-lake-plain-section&#34;&gt;2A. Chicago Lake Plain Section&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once covered by glacial Lake Chicago; consists of nearly level lacustrine silt and clay deposits. Mesic and wet prairie and marsh originally extensive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;2b-gary-lake-plain-section&#34;&gt;2B. Gary Lake Plain Section&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Includes the Tolleston, Calumet, and Glenwood beach ridges and intervening often slightly acidic sand flats. Characterized by sand savannas with intervening wet sand prairies and marshes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;2c-benton-harbor-lake-plain-section&#34;&gt;2C. Benton Harbor Lake Plain Section&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Topographically similar to &lt;a href=&#34;https://ettedh.github.io/texts/plants-chicago-region/#2b-gary-lake-plain-section&#34;&gt;2B&lt;/a&gt;, but originally mostly wooded with rich swamps and mesic forests.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;2d-illinois-dunes-section&#34;&gt;2D. Illinois Dunes Section&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Low beach ridges and swales at Illinois Beach State Park and Chiwaukee Prairie support an open community of sand prairie, sand savanna, and marsh. Two additional sand areas of irregular shape which once existed on the lake plain were probably similar; these are within the present limits of Evanston and Chicago.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;2e-ridge-and-swale-section&#34;&gt;2E. Ridge and Swale Section&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Formed only within the past 6000 years, characterized by alternating parallel low ridges and swales. Ridges consist of relatively alkaline sandy soils and are covered by sand prairie and a sparse savanna of black oak and jack pines, wetlands characterized by pannes and open water.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;2f-high-dune-section&#34;&gt;2F. High Dune Section&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Narrow band along Lake Michigan; includes a unique high dune complex of communities.  Prevailing winds which build the dunes also bring higher than normal snowfall, moderate temperatures, and new sand.  Regularly timbered with black oak and white pine savanna, becoming more regularly forested northward.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;grand-prairie-natural-division&#34;&gt;Grand Prairie Natural Division&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The grand prairie once covered much of east-central Illinois. The northeastern portion of this natural region enters the Chicago region.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;3a-grand-prairie-section&#34;&gt;3A. Grand Prairie Section&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mostly end and ground moraines; level to gently rolling. Characterized by taligrass prairie, with timbered communities limited to the margins of rivers and well-drained morainic ridges.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;3b-kankakee-sand-section&#34;&gt;3B. Kankakee Sand Section&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Aeolian and lacustrine sand deposits, mostly on the south side of the Kankakee River.  Sand savannas are frequent on dunes, interspersed with wet to dry sand prairie, sand flatwoods, marsh, and shrub swamps.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;3c-kankakee-marsh-section&#34;&gt;3C. Kankakee Marsh Section&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Vast wetlands which once bordered the Kankakee River in Indiana; marsh was probably the predominant community type, areas of true swamp and riparian savanna were present.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;3d-bedrock-valley-section&#34;&gt;3D. Bedrock Valley Section&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dolomite exposed along the Des Plaines River by scouring from the outflow of glacial Lake Chicago. The Kankakee torrent cut down to underlying dolomite from Momence to the confluence with the Des Plaines. In the Illinois River Valley, shale and sandstone exposures are more prevalent. Unique communities include dolomite cliffs and prairie, typically interspersed with sedge meadow and marsh.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;glacial-lakes-natural-division&#34;&gt;Glacial Lakes Natural Division&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Only one section of the Northern Lakes Division enters the eastern part of our region.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;4a-glacial-lakes-section&#34;&gt;4A. Glacial Lakes Section&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Exhibits complex and uneven ice-contact terrain deposited by a stagnating glacier.&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref1:3&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Moraines, kames, and outwash plains are present, and kettle ponds, lakes, and swamps are numerous. Extensive forests, with savannas on steep slopes. Lakes, swamps, bogs, fens, and marshes are interspersed.  This section is expanded to include a gravel outwash fan, formerly mapped as part of &lt;a href=&#34;https://ettedh.github.io/texts/plants-chicago-region/#3b-kankakee-sand-section&#34;&gt;3B&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;natural-plant-communitites&#34;&gt;Natural Plant Communitites&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Chicago region, situated at the southern end of Lake Michigan, lies along the northeastern edge of the Tall Grass Prairie biome of the Midwest. The prevailing landscape at the time of settlement was open prairie. In some areas the prairie was flat, in others rolling.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Undoubtedly, the most remarkable feature of the state of Illinois is its extensive prairies, or non-wooded tracts. They begin on a comparatively small scale in the basin of lake Erie, and already form the bluff of the land about lake Michigan, the Upper Wabash, and the Illinois, &amp;hellip; or rather, the whole of this tract may be described as prairie intersected by patches of woodland, chiefly confined to the river valleys. The characteristic peculiarity of the prairies is the absence of timber; in other respects, they present all the varieties of soil and surface that are found elsewhere; some are of inexhaustible fertility, others of hopeless sterility; some spread out in vast boundless plains, others are undulating or rolling, while others are broken by hills. In general, they are covered with a rich growth of grass, forming excellent natural meadows, from which circumstance they take their name. &lt;em&gt;Prairie&lt;/em&gt; is a French word, signifying &lt;em&gt;meadow&lt;/em&gt;, and is applied to any description of surface that is destitute of timber and brushwood, and clothed with grass. Wet, dry, level, and undulating, are terms of description merely, and apply to prairies in the same sense as they do to forest lands. The prairies of Illinois may be classed under three general divisions;&amp;ndash;the healthy, or bushy; the alluvial, or wet; and the dry, or undulating.  Those [that] have springs of water, &amp;hellip; are covered with bushes of hazel and furze, small sassafras shrubs interspersed with grape-vine, and in the season of flowers become beautifully decorated by a rich profusion of gay herbaceous plants.&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:6&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:6&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The prairies were regularly interspersed with poorly drained flatland, and the hills were commonly characterized by hanging fens and seepage slopes where the water-filled high grounds discharged a constant flow of clear water into wet meadows and marshes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Between the Plein and Theakaki, the country is flat, wet, and swampy, interspersed with prairies of an inferior quality of soil.&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:7&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:7&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Throughout the region were small to large tracts of savannas consisting of open-grown timbers, mostly of Bur and White Oak. Eastward, around the southern tip of Lake Michigan, the lake shore rose up in high wooded dunes covered mostly in White Pine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The northern part of Illinois is beautifully diversified with groves of timber and rolling prairies. The shores of Michigan have a large supply of pine timber, and from this source the lumber for buildings at Chicago is obtained. &amp;hellip; The stage road, from Michigan City to Chicago, is, most of the way, on the sandy beach. Chicago &amp;hellip; is built on a level prairie, open in full view to the Lake, and the soil is enough mixed with sand, to prevent its being muddy.&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:8&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:8&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;hellip; there were along where Michigan Avenue now is walled with palatial mansions innumerable sand hills rising to a considerable height, overrun by the wild juniper loaded with its fragrant berries at the feet of which stretched away to the southeast the soft smooth beach of firm glistening sand &amp;hellip; along the beach north of the river where also the drifting sand has been piled by the shifting winds into a thousand hills stretching farther back from the waters than on the south, but here the juniper bush was replaced by a stunted growth of scraggy pines often hilled up by the drifting sand. &amp;hellip; Further back was a broad ramble among stately oaks sparsely scattered over the even plain among which a horseman could be seen at a great distance.&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:9&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:9&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;9&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Behind the dunes were vast wet prairies and marshes, which, eastward and northward, gave way to huge swamps of mixed hardwood forests. East of the windward shores, in the lee of the dunes and beyond, the timbers closed up in spots into tighter savannas and cool forests of Sugar Maple and Beech; but the timbers soon opened up again into scattered groves and prairies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the one hand stretched bur-oak plains, spread with a verdant carpet, variegated with dazzling wild flowers, without an obstacle to intercept the view for miles, save the sombre trunks of the low oaks, sparsely spreading their shadows across the lawn; on the other hand arose the undulations of the white oak openings, with picturesque outlines of swales and slopes gracefully sweeping and sharply defined in the distance. Then, there lay the majestic prairie, grand in expansive solitude, its fringe of timber, as seen in the distance, resembling a diligently trained and well-trimmed garden parterre.&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:10&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:10&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;10&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Southward and westward, the landscape was broken by large streams, with flat prairie bottoms and scattered stretches of tree-lined bluffs and backwaters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The roads in this country are in a state of nature, But the ground is so smooth, and so entirely free from stones, that when the earth is dry you do not find better roads at the north. &amp;hellip; We took the Galena road, forded the river, a stream about four rods wide, and passed on, over a beautiful, open prairie country, here and there a log house, a small grove of timber, or small stream of water; the land high, dry and rich, and arrived at night at Naper’s settlement, on the Du Page River, thirty-seven miles from Chicago. &amp;hellip; We now left the Galena road and took a course more northerly to the Big and Little Woods, on [the] Fox River. In travelling twelve miles we came to the settiement, at the lower end of &amp;ldquo;Little Woods.&amp;rdquo; &amp;hellip; houses were built near the timber, and a beautiful rich prairie opened before them.  &amp;hellip; [The] Fox River is a clear stream of water, about twenty rods wide, having a hard limestone bottom, from two to three feet deep, a brisk current, and generally fordable. On its banks, and on some other streams, we occasionally found ledges of limestone; but other than that, we found no rocks in the State. We here forded the river, and travelled all day on its western bank. We found less timber on this side of the river. On the east side, it is generally lined with timber to the depth of a mile or more; but the west side is scarcely skirted with it. It is somewhat singular and unaccountable, but we found it universally to be the fact, that the east side of all the streams had much the largest portion of timber.&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref1:8&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:8&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All of the streams in the northern parts of the state, which empty into the Wabash and Illinois, have their branches interwoven with many of the rivers running into lake Erie and Michigan. &amp;hellip; [T]hey not unfrequently issue from the same marsh, prairie, pond, or lake. The &amp;hellip; portage between the Chicago and the Kickapoo [Des Plaines] branch of the Illinois, [is] rendered important by the inundations, which at certain seasons cover the intermediate prairie, from which the two opposite streams flow. By this means nature herself opened a navigable communication between the Great Lakes and the Mississippi; and it is a fact, however difficult it may be of belief to many, that boats not unfrequently pass from Lake Michigan into the Illinois, and in some instances without being subjected to the necessity of having their lading taken out.&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref1:7&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:7&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The country back of Chicago, for the distance of twelve miles, is a smooth, level prairie; producing an abundance of grass, but too low and wet for cultivation. The Chicago River is formed by two branches, which meet at the upper end of the village. The branches come from exactly opposite directions and after running some distance, parallel with the lake, and about a mile from it, here meet each other, and turning at right angles, flow in a regular straight channel, like a canal, into the lake. On each side of the town, between these branches and the lake shore, there is, for some distance, a good growth of wood and timber. On the lake shore, there are naked sand hills; and these are found all around the lake.  &amp;hellip; If Lake Michigan were ten feet higher than its present level, its waters would flow into the Illinois river. The Oplanes, a branch of the Illinois, approaches within twelve miles of the Lake; and the land between is low and level. When the water is high, boats now pass from the lake to the river. At a time of high water, a steamboat attempted to pass from the Illinois to the lake. After running a day from Ottawa up the river, the water began to subside, the captain became alarmed, lest his boat might run aground and returned.&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref2:8&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:8&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The alluvial, or wet prairies, are generally on the margins of the great water courses, though sometimes they are at a distance from them; their soil is deep, black, friable, and of exhaustless fertility. &amp;hellip;  From May to October, the prairies are covered with tall grass and flower-producing weeds. In June and July, they seem like an ocean of flowers of various hues, waving to the breezes which sweep over them.  The numerous tall flowering shrubs and vegetables which grow luxuriantly over these plains, present a striking and delightful appearance.&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref1:6&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:6&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The landscape was replete with wet depressions, and, particularly northwestward in our region, surrounded by copses of larch, and then by shrubs and sedge meadows. Such landscapes were burned on a regular basis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The dry or undulating prairies are almost destitute of springs and of all vegetation, with the exception of weeds, flowers, and grass. The undulations are so slight that, to the eye, the surface has almost the appearance of an uninterrupted level, though the ravines made by freshets show that there is a considerable degree of inclination. In the prairie region there are numerous ponds, formed some from the surface water, the effect of rain, and the melting of the snows in the spring and others near the rivers from their overflowing.&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref2:6&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:6&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The prairies are all burnt over once a year, either in spring or fall, but generally in the fall; and the fire is undoubtedly, the true cause of the origin and continuance of them. In passing through the State I saw many of them on fire; and in the night, it was the grandest exhibition I ever saw. A mountain of flame, 30 feet high, and of unknown length, moving onward, roaring like &amp;lsquo;many waters’&amp;ndash;in a gently, stately movement, and unbroken front&amp;ndash;then impelled by a gust of wind, suddenly breaks itself to pieces, here and there shooting ahead, whirling itself high in air&amp;ndash;all becomes noise, and strife, and uproar, and disorder. Well might Black Hawk look with indifference on the puny exhibition of fireworks in New York, when he had so often seen fireworks displayed, on such a gigantic scale, on his own native prairies.&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref3:8&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:8&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For most writers today, our landscape no longer evokes such eloquence. To the extent that the natural landscape is described at all, it is done so very clinically, mostly yielding codifications of plant communities. Such taxonomies are facilitated by the fact that our natural communities are fragmented into disparate pieces, with many of the intervening, and possibly confounding, communities gone forever.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Attempting to discriminate plant communities from among the myriad of plant associations is, nonetheless, a pursuit of botanists seeking to assign each plant a &amp;ldquo;proper&amp;rdquo; and definable place in the landscape. Part of the challenge is to give each community a name which consists of two or three words from the English dictionary. Commonly used words include nouns such as &lt;em&gt;forest&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;swamp&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;savanna&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;flatwoods&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;prairie&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;meadow&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;fen&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;bog&lt;/em&gt;, and adjectives such as &lt;em&gt;acidic&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;alkaline&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;wet&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;mesic&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;dry&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;sandy&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;mucky&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;loamy&lt;/em&gt;. The difficulty begins when the default assumption is made that if the words do not exist, the community cannot exist. In the taxon entries we have avoided forcing the native species into formally circumscribed plant communities, choosing instead to use common English prose and a list of immediate associates to describe the habitat. While our native plants are prevailingly faithful to some natural context, a disciplined attempt to place even a small percentage of the 1,638 elements into one or more formally designated categories, however permutated, quickly informs the botanist of the folly of this exercise.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another factor complicating plant community classification is the fact that soon after the Native American culture was replaced by the European culture changes in the human relationship with the landscape caused fundamental changes in plant community composition. Cessation of fire, straightening of rivers, ditching, tiling, heavy grazing, and urban and suburban infrastructure have so modified the original structure and depauperized the land that our ability to piece together an understanding of natural order is profoundly compromised. About 90 percent of our native flora is restricted to the stable habitats provided by our original plant communities,&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:11&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:11&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;11&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; so an understanding and stewardship of such areas is critical if we are to carry forward into the future a possibility of association with living things other than ourselves, a few weeds, and cultivars.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Given all the problems associated with trying to envision and describe the natural plant communities, we nevertheless will propose a paradigm of plant communities. While these communities are certainly more artifacts of binary thinking than representative of nature, a brief synopsis can communicate to a botanist information on the nature of our flora and landscape. An intellectual miscarriage occurs only when it is pretended that such community constructs are or could be &amp;ldquo;scientifically&amp;rdquo; abstracted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Generally, one can visualize about nine principal kinds of communities: aquatic, marsh, fen, bog, swamp, forest, savanna, dune, and prairie. With the exception of certain dune, bedrock, or coastal-plain disjunct systems, most of these general community groups are variously expressed in the different natural divisions and sections (see page 38). In choosing representative species, we have generally chosen a few very conservative species to which the user can refer in the annotated checklist for further associates and nuances of habit, distribution, and more detailed interpretations of the plant community. These representative species are not intended to represent associations for specific kinds of plant communities; rather, each species tends to represent a facet or variant of the general community type. The word &amp;ldquo;characteristic,&amp;rdquo; when used in connection with species listed under the community descriptions, does not necessarily mean that the species are common or even locally extant in the community; rather, it is meant to imply that the species are typical of or restricted to the community, and that habitat discussions under those species in the annotated checklist amplify the character of the community. Another type of natural community in the Chicago region is the ruderal flora, principally those species with &lt;em&gt;C&lt;/em&gt; values 0 or 1.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;aquatic&#34;&gt;Aquatic&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Aquatic plant communities were occasional throughout the region but most abundant in our eastern and northwestern sectors. They formed in the landscape in potholes and in lacustrine plains where there was no discharge. Since our region evaporates nearly or quite as much water as falls, aquatic communities are sustained by waters from a surrounding watershed in excess of that provided by rain over their surfaces. Generally, these excess waters filter down through vegetated ground into the underlying soil until they reach impervious material, and exit by way of springs, rills, or ground water. Along our major streams, aquatic plant communities developed in alluvial sloughs and ponds derived from surface melt or runoff waters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The more minerotrophic or ground-water communities are characterized by plants such as &lt;em&gt;Brasenia schreberi&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Hippuris vulgaris&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Megalodonta beckii&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Myriophyllum verticillatum pectinatum&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Potamogeton amplifolius&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Potamogeton richardsonii&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Potamogeton strictifolius&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Utricularia vulgaris&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;Zannichellia palustris&lt;/em&gt;. In softer waters one is more likely to encounter plants such as &lt;em&gt;Nuphar advena&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Nuphar variegatum&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Nymphaea tuberosa&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Utricularia geminiscapa&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;Utricularia purpurea&lt;/em&gt;. Alluvial or surface water communities are characterized by members of the &lt;em&gt;Lemnaceae&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Ceratophyllum demersum&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Potamogeton foliosus&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Potamogeton pectinatus&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Potamogeton illinoensis&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;Potamogeton natans&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;marsh&#34;&gt;Marsh&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Marsh plant communities generally occur along the transition between aquatic communities and drier communities, or in large flats which are regularly inundated by shallow surface waters for much of the growing season. Marshes are best developed with us in the Lake Plain, in the lacustrine flats of our northwestern and eastern sectors, and along the lower reaches of the Des Plaines and Kankakee river drainages. These communities are best characterized by emergent species such as &lt;em&gt;Carex aquatilis&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Carex lacustris&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Hydrocotyle umbellata&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Hypericum boreale&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Peltandra virginica&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Pontederia cordata&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Sagittaria graminea&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Sagittaria latifolia&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Sagittaria rigida&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Scirpus subterminalis&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Scirpus validus creber&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Sparganium americanum&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Sparganium chlorocarpum&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Sparganium eurycarpum&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;Zizania aquatica&lt;/em&gt;. On the shores of ponds, lakes, and swales, often growing without heavy competition, conservative species include &lt;em&gt;Cyperus diandrus&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Eleocharis geniculata&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Juncus pelocarpus&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Peplis diandra&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Rotala ramosior&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Scirpus purshianus&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Scirpus torreyi&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Sparganium chlorocarpum&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Utricularia gibba&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Veronica comosa&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;Veronica scutellata&lt;/em&gt;. A related community, with affinities to fens and wet prairies, is the sedge meadow. It develops in large, shallow, lacustrine flats, and is dominated by hummocks of sedges, particularly &lt;em&gt;Carex stricta&lt;/em&gt;, and characterized by conservative species such as &lt;em&gt;Aster puniceus&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Carex buxbaumii&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Carex atriculata&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Dulichium arundinaceum&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Lysimachia terrestris&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Lysimachia thyrsiflora&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Rumex orbiculatus&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Sium suave&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;Utricularia vulgaris&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;fen&#34;&gt;Fen&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fens are wetland communities which occur in areas where the glacial formations are such that carbonate-rich ground water discharges at a constant rate along the slopes of kames, eskers, moraines, river bluffs, or even dunes, or in flats associated with these formations, provided the material through which the waters traveled is rich in calcium or magnesium carbonates. Depending upon the circumstances fens can occur where marl is at or near the surface or where peats are constantly bathed in minerotrophic ground water; such areas can be wooded or open.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Marly fens are commonly on open prairie slopes and are characterized by &lt;em&gt;Carex sterilis&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Eleocharis rostellata&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Rhynchospora capillacea&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Scirpus cespitosus callosus&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Tofieldia glutinosa&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;Triglochin palustris&lt;/em&gt;. In the constantly flowing rills discharging in these fens grow &lt;em&gt;Agrostis alba palustris&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Armoracia aquatica&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Berula erecta&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;Mimulus glabratus fremontii&lt;/em&gt;. Related to the hillside fens are the wooded seeps which occur sporadically on steep bluffs. Characteristic species include &lt;em&gt;Aster prenanthoides&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Cimicifuga racemosa&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Fraxinus nigra&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Polymnia canadensis&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Rhamnus alnifolia&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Rhamnus lanceolata&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Thuja occidentalis&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Ulmus thomasii&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;Veronica americana&lt;/em&gt;. As fens become peatier characteristic species include &lt;em&gt;Betula pumila&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Campanula uliginosa&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Conioselinum chinense&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Eriophorum angustifolium&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Filipendula rubra&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Galium asprellum&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Habenaria lacera&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Phlox maculata&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Pogonia ophioglossoides&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Patentilla fruticosa&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Salix candida&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Saxifraga pensylvanica&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Solidago uliginosa&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;Valeriana uliginosa&lt;/em&gt;.  The flat, black-soil prairie fens are characterized by &lt;em&gt;Aster borealis&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Carex interior&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Carex prairea&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Cirsium muticum&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Cypripedium candidum&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Habenaria hyperborea huronensis&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Lobelia kalmii&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Muhlenbergia glamerata&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Parnassia glauca&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Satureja arkansana&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Scleria verticillata&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Selaginella apoda&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;and Valeriana ciliata&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;bog&#34;&gt;Bog&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Bog&lt;/em&gt;, like most of the other terms used here to describe plant communities, is not a scientific word in the sense that its use always signifies a uniform, unique concept which is standardly perceived. Any place, for example, where there is a quagmire or wet, mucky, hummocky ground is likely to be termed a &amp;ldquo;bog;&amp;rdquo; hence, the expression &amp;ldquo;bogged down.&amp;rdquo; The contemporary ecologist tends to restrict the term &amp;ldquo;bog&amp;rdquo; to a hydric/edaphic vegetational scenario which is typified by acidic, usually organic substrates, and a characteristic floristic composition. Many of our peatlands are influenced significantly by waters rich in carbonates and can be called prairie fens. But as the cation exchange capacity damps off bog-like conditions can begin to develop. Many of the bogs in our northwestern sector can be called alkaline bogs for that reason.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Commonly the peatland floats on a minerotrophic head of water, with the deeper roots thus exposed to calcareous or circumneutral conditions, and the shallower roots are imbedded in the upper sphagnum mat, probably in a more acidic environment. Characteristic species in these minerotrophic or alkaline bogs include &lt;em&gt;Carex brunnescens&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Carex diandra&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Carex lasiocarpa americana&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Carex leptalea&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Geum rivale&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Hypericum virginicum fraseri&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Larix laricina&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Menyanthes trifoliata minor&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Potentilla palustris&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Rhus vernix&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Rhynchospora alba&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Ribes hirtellum&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Salix pedicellaris hypoglauca&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Salix serissima&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Sarracenia purpurea&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Utricularia intermedia&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;Utricularia minor&lt;/em&gt;. In large basins or in areas where the influence of minerotrophic waters is insignificant, characteristically acid bogs can develop, inhabited by plants such as &lt;em&gt;Andromeda glaucophylla&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Arethusa bulbosa&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Carex atlantica capillacea&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Carex canescens&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Carex chordorrhiza&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Carex disperma&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Carex echinata&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Carex limosa&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Carex oligosperma&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Carex pauciflora&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Carex tenuiflora&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Carex trisperma&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Chamaedaphne calyculata angustifolia&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Cypripedium acaule&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Drosera intermedia&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Drosera rotundifolia&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Eriophorum gracile&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Eriophorum spissum&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Eriophorum virginicum&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Habenaria blephariglottis&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Habenaria ciliaris&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Hypericum virginicum&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Salix sericea&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Scheuchzeria palustris americana&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Utricularia geminiscapa&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Vaccinium macrocarpon&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Vaccinium oxycoccos&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Viola pallens&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;Woodwardia virginica&lt;/em&gt;. Related to the acid bog, often in sand flats or basins, are floating sedge mats that rise and fall with the water table. Such mats are characterized by &lt;em&gt;Eleocharis robbinsii&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Eriocaulon septangulare&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Fuirena pumila&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Hypericum canadense&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Rhexia virginica&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;Scirpus smithii&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;swamp&#34;&gt;Swamp&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Swamps are wetlands characterized by trees growing in large flats or basins that are poorly drained, with most of the water leaving through evapotranspiration. They can occur in the backwaters of large, slow moving rivers, such as the Kankakee, or in wet sandy flats in the Kankakee Sand Section south of the Valparaiso Moraine. They also occur on the moraine in wet depressions. North of the Valparaiso Moraine, in the Lake Plain, they are best developed in the large flats behind the high dunes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Along the Kankakee River they occur in bottomlands, with characteristic species including &lt;em&gt;Carex typhina&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Cephalanthus occidentalis&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Fraxinus pennsylvanica subintegerrima&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Fraxinus tomentosa&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Mikania scandens&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Populus heterophylla&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;Styrax americana&lt;/em&gt;. In sandy, poorly drained flats with a high water table, a fire-dependent savanna-like swamp dominated by &lt;em&gt;Quercus palustris&lt;/em&gt; is characterized by &lt;em&gt;Bartonia virginica&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Betula nigra&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Carex haydenii&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Carex longii&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Carex straminea&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Eleocharis tenuis verrucosa&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;Rubus hispidus&lt;/em&gt;. On the moraines, especially the Valparaiso and Lake Border moraines, there are shallow depressions characterized by &lt;em&gt;Quercus bicolor&lt;/em&gt;; other characteristic species include &lt;em&gt;Carex crus-corvi&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Carex lupuliformis&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Carex muskingumensis&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Carex squarrosa&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Carex tuckermanii&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Carex vesicaria monile&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Cephalanthus occidentalis&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Fraxinus nigra&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Onoclea sensibilis&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;Lycopus rubellus&lt;/em&gt;. There is a phase of this swamp on the low terraces of the Kankakee River, characterized by &lt;em&gt;Carex grayii&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Carex lupulina&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Carex muskingumensis&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Leersia lenticularis&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Lysimachia hybrida&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;Quercus bicolor&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the broad low flats behind the high dunesof Lake Michigan lies one of the richest and most complicated forested systems in our region. It is characterized by a complex hydrology and is interspersed by gentle rises, shallow depressions, and hummocks, and consists of an inseparable mixture of wooded fen, bog, and mesic forest. It supports a wide array of species, including trees such as &lt;em&gt;Acer saccharum&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Betula alleghaniensis&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Betula papyrifera&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Fagus grandifolia&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Quercus bicolor&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Quercus palustris&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Quercus rubra&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;Tilia americana&lt;/em&gt;; other characteristic species include &lt;em&gt;Carex bromoides&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Carex crinita&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Carex debilis rudgei&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Carex folliculata&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Carex intumescens&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Carex seorsa&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Chrysosplenium americanum&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Coptis trifolia&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Cypripedium calceolus pubescens&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Dryopteris cristata&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Habenaria clavellata&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Habenaria flava herbiola&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Habenaria psycodes&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Lycopodium lucidulum&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Lycopodium obscurum&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Medeola virginiana&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Milium effusum&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Nemopanthus mucronata&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Poa paludigena&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Rubus pubescens&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Trientalis borealis&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;Viola incognita&lt;/em&gt;. Such swamps, while they retain their essential characteristics, change in specific species composition as one travels northeastward from Dune Acres in Porter County to Benton Harbor in Berrien County.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;forest&#34;&gt;Forest&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Forests occur in our eastern sector on rises which are relatively well drained and physiographically located such that exposure to fire is rare. Such forests are dominated by &lt;em&gt;Acer saccharum&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Fagus grandifolia&lt;/em&gt;. The ground cover vegetation is not physiognomically capable of sustaining a line of fire.  Characteristic species include &lt;em&gt;Athyrium pycnocarpon&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Athyrium thelypterioides&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Carex amphibola&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Carex careyana&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Carex deweyana&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Carex digitalis&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Carex laxiflora&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Carex leptonervia&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Carex plantaginea&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Carex prasina&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Corallorhiza maculata&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Cornus rugosa&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Dentaria diphylla&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Dicentra canadensis&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Dirca palustris&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Dryopteris hexagonoptera&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Dryopteris marginalis&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Dryopteris noveboracensis&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Galium circaezans&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Galium lanceolatum&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Hieracium paniculatum&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Hydrophyllum canadense&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Lonicera canadensis&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Maianthemum canadense&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Mitella diphylla&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Panax trifolius&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Panicum commutatum ashei&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Panicum dichotomum&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Poa alsodes&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Pyrola asarifolia purpurea&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Sambucus pubens&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Tipularia discolor&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;Viola rostrata&lt;/em&gt;. Another type of forest is along the high dunes, northward in Berrien County, characterized by &lt;em&gt;Betula alleghaniensis&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Cornus rugosa&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Dirca palustris&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Fagus grandifolia&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Taxus canadensis&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;Tsuga canadensis&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A relative of our eastern forest occurs on the western bluff of Lake Michigan in the deep morainic dissections or ravines. Here also grow &lt;em&gt;Acer saccharum&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Fagus grandifolia&lt;/em&gt;, but the ground cover vegetation is such that sporadic ground fires could creep down the slopes from the savannas on the higher, more level ground, and nose slopes. Characteristic species include &lt;em&gt;Betula papyrifera&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Carex pedunculata&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Dryopteris filix-mas&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Matteuccia struthiopteris&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Poa languida&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Populus balsamifera&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Prunus nigra&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Pyrola elliptica&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;Shepherdia canadensis&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Pinus resinosa&lt;/em&gt; may also have grown here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;savanna&#34;&gt;Savanna&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Savannas, as interpreted here, include those portions of our wooded landscape in which structure was, to one degree or another, affected by fires set by Native Americans in the thousands of years before European settlement. Generally, these communities were intercalated among the prairies and developed a ground-cover vegetation which would carry at least occasional fires in the autumn, when their surrounding prairies were wont to burn. Such savannas ranged in character from completely closed and forest-like, to very open with only scattered trees.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most related to the forest communities are mesic savannas. These are closed-canopy woodlands, dominated by &lt;em&gt;Acer nigrum&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Quercus rubra&lt;/em&gt;, and with a graminoid ground cover capable of sustaining small but occasional ground fires. Such savannas are best developed on north- and east-facing slopes in dissected or topographically complex portions of the moraines. Characteristic species include &lt;em&gt;Actaea rubra&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Adiantum pedatum&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Agrimonia rostellata&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Arabis canadensis&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Aralia racemosa&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Aristolochia serpentaria&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Aster furcatus&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Aureolaria virginica&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Brachyelytrum erectum&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Carex gracillima&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Carex hitchcockiana&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Carex laxiculmis&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Carex shortiana&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Carex woodii&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Cercis canadensis&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Collinsia verna&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Conopholis americana&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Diarrhena americana&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Dryopteris goldiana&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Habenaria viridis bracteata&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Jeffersonia diphylla&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Linum virginianum&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Lonicera dioica&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Morus rubra&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Muhlenbergia sylvatica&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Orchis spectabilis&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Poa sylvestris&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Sanicula trifoliata&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Scutellaria ovata versicolor&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;Trillium grandifiorum&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the more undulating, well drained, but fertile morainic ridges and knolls are the dry-mesic savannas dominated by &lt;em&gt;Quercus alba&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Quercus macrocarpa&lt;/em&gt;. It is probable that portions of such woodlands burned fairly regularly, and carried low but steady lines of flame. Characteristic species include &lt;em&gt;Agalinis gattingeri&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Arenaria lateriflora&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Aster schreberi&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Bromus purgans&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Camassia scilloides&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Carex hirtifolia&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Carex oligocarpa&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Carex pensylvanica&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Carya ovata&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Corylus americana&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Dodecatheon meadia&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Erigeron pulchellus&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Eupatorium sessilifolium brittonianum&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Helianthemum bicknellii&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Heuchera richardsonii&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Hystrix patula&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Krigia biflora&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Lathyrus ochroleucus&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Lechea intermedia&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Monotropa uniflora&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Orobanche uniflora&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Silene virginica&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Swertia caroliniensis&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Taenidia integerrima&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Trillium sessile&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;Vici caroliniana&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the nearly level or gently undulating moraines are the open savannas of heavier soil characterized by open-grown trees of &lt;em&gt;Quercus macrocarpa&lt;/em&gt;. Such savannas have a well developed graminoid ground cover, and carry substantial fires on a regular basis. These savannas developed on low mounds within the mesic or wet prairies, or in transitional zones between the lower prairies and the dry prairies of kames and eskers. Little is known about the conservative flora of these savannas, but species which we associate with the Bur Oak include &lt;em&gt;Andropogon gerardii&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Carex pensylvanica&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Carya ovata&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Corylus americana&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Galium concinnum&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Helianthus hirsutus&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Hypoxis hirsuta&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Lilium michiganense&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Rosa setigera&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Solidago juncea&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Thalictrum dasycarpum&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Trillium recurvatum&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;Veronicastrum virginicum&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In sandy soils, especially in our eastern sector, along well drained ridges and old dunes, the savannas are dominated by Quercus velutina. Such savannas are closely associated with sand prairies, and the two communities have many species in common. The sand savannas burn regularly and are characterized by species such as &lt;em&gt;Aralia hispida&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Aster linariifolius&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Baptisia tinctoria crebra&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Campanula rotundifolia&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Carex siccata&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Chimaphila umbellata cisatlantica&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Corydalis sempervirens&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Galium pilosum&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Liatris aspera&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Lysimachia quadrifolia&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Monotropa hypopithys&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Pteridium aquilinum latiusculum&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Rubus enslenii&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Spiranthes lacera&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;Vaccinium angustifolium&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It would seem that there is a close association between the sand savannas and what once were pine savannas near the southern shore of Lake Michigan, where &lt;em&gt;Pinus strobus&lt;/em&gt; was plentiful along the dunes.  There remain a few isolated stands where one can only imagine what species once characterized these pine savannas. It was probably in these pine savannas wherein resided such now rare plants as &lt;em&gt;Arctostaphylos uva-ursi coactilis&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Epigaea repens&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Habenaria hookeri&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Lactuca hirsuta&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Melampyrum lineare latifolium&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Oryzopsis pungens&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;Polygala paucifolia&lt;/em&gt;. Probably also included here are the associates of &lt;em&gt;Carex eburnea&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Celtis tenuifolia&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Chimaphila maculata&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Juniperus communis&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Oryzopsis asperifolia&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;Pyrola rotundifolia americana&lt;/em&gt;. Farther north, along the high dunes, the pine savannas give way to a wooded dune forest.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;dune&#34;&gt;Dune&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the open sand of foredunes of Lake Michigan is a special habitat characterized by species which grow locally only in the dunes near the lake. These include &lt;em&gt;Ammophila breviligulata&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Cakile edentula&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Cirsium pitcheri&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Euphorbia polygonifolia&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Lathyrus japonicus glaber&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Salix syrticola&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;Solidago racemosa gillmanii&lt;/em&gt;. Confined to the lower dunes along the western shore of Lake Michigan is &lt;em&gt;Juniperus horizontalis&lt;/em&gt;. In the more active sands in the dunes of our eastern sector grow &lt;em&gt;Hudsonia tomentosa&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Polygonella articulata&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;Selaginella rupestris&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In wet, interdunal flats (pannes), where sand has been blown out down to the water table, is a plant community generally characterized by species such as &lt;em&gt;Carex aurea&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Carex garberi&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Gentiana crinita&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Hypericum kalmianum&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Sabatia angularis&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Triglochin maritima&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;Utricularia cornuta&lt;/em&gt;. The pannes near Ogden Dunes, Porter County, are characteristically surrounded by small forests of Pinus banksiana.  Related to both the pannes and the prairie fens is a kind of wet alkaline prairie, characterized by plants such as &lt;em&gt;Agalinis skinneriana&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Carex conoidea&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Carex crawei&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Carex flava&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Carex viridula&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Castilleja coccinea&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Cladium mariscoides&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Cypripedium calceolus parviflorum&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Eleocharis compressa&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Panicum boreale&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;Scleria triglomerata&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;prairie&#34;&gt;Prairie&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The prairies comprise those plant communities that are dominated by a diversity of perennial forbs growing in a perennial graminoid matrix, which forms a dry flammable turf in autumn. A part of the habitat of our prairies was the regular autumnal fire, which, lacking a regular occurrence of dry lightning, was set annually by the Native Americans. Prairies developed on those substrates in which the aboveground perennial phytomass produced more fixed carbon annually than was likely to be grazed or decomposed. In our area prairie communities range from wet to dry and once dominated much of the landscape, intercalating or even blending with savannas and fens.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To a Midwesterner, perhaps the first image evoked with the term prairie is that of the tall grasses of &lt;em&gt;Andropogon gerardii&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Sorghastrum nutans&lt;/em&gt; in their full, late-summer development&amp;ndash;&amp;ldquo;high as a man on a horse,&amp;rdquo; interspersed with the rosinweeds, sunflowers, and asters. Such are the mesic prairies; conservative species within them include &lt;em&gt;Baptisia leucophaea&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Cacalia plantaginea&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Carex bicknellii&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Eryngium yuccifolium&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Gentiana andrewsii&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Gentiana puberulenta&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Habenaria leucophaea&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Lilium philadelphicum andinum&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Panicum leibergii&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Sisyrinchium albidum&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;Sporobolus heterolepis&lt;/em&gt;. A wetter variant of the mesic prairie is more likely to be dominated by &lt;em&gt;Calamagrostis canadensis&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Spartina pectinata&lt;/em&gt;, with &lt;em&gt;Aster puniceus firmus&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Beckmannia syzigachne&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Chelone glabra&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Eleocharis wolfii&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Lysimachia quadriflora&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Oenothera perennis&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Oenothera pilosella&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Pedicularis lanceolata&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;Solidago ohioensis&lt;/em&gt;, and in its best development is fen-like.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the drier prairies &lt;em&gt;Andropogon scoparius&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Stipa spartea&lt;/em&gt; are commonly the more obvious grasses, with conservative species including &lt;em&gt;Agalinis aspera&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Asclepias viridiflora&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Aster ptarmicoides&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Aster sericeus&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Astragalus tennesseensis&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Blephilia ciliata&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Bromus kalmii&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Carex meadii&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Cirsium hillii&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Convolvulus spithamaeus&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Helianthus occidentalis&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Panicum perlongum&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Polytaenia nuttallii&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Psoralea tenuifoa&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Zizia aptera&lt;/em&gt;. Another kind of dry prairie occurs in the Kettle Moraine Section, or our northwestern sector and, growing among short warm-season grasses like &lt;em&gt;Bouteloua curtipendula&lt;/em&gt;, characteristic species include &lt;em&gt;Agoseris cuspidata&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Allium stellatum&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Anemone patens wolfgangiana&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Artemisia serrata&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Asclepias lanuginosa&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Blephilia ciliata&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Carex richardsonii&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Geum triflorum&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Houstonia longifolia&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Oenothera serrulata&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Panicum wilcoxianum&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Potentilla pensylvanica bipinnatifida&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Ranunculus rhomboideus&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Sisyrinchium campestre&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;Wulfenia bullii&lt;/em&gt;. Another variant of the dry prairie occurs on the dolomitic bedrock pavements exposed along our major rivers, particularly the lower Des Plaines; characteristic species are &lt;em&gt;Actinea herbacea&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Arenaria patula&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Deschampsia caespitosa glauca&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Muhlenbergia cuspidata&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Petalostemum foliosum&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;Scutellaria parvula&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A major variant of the dry prairie is the sand prairie, in which the principal fuel species is commonly &lt;em&gt;Andropogon scoparius&lt;/em&gt;; in many respects it seems scarcely more than an exaggerated opening in the sand savanna. Characteristic species include &lt;em&gt;Asclepias hirtella&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Astragalus canadensis&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Callirhoë triangulata&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Carex muhlenbergii&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Ceanothus herbaceus&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Commelina erecta deamiana&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Desmodium ciliare&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Fimbristylis puberula&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Orobanche fasciculata&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;Sisyrinchium montanum&lt;/em&gt;. In moist to wet, acid sandy flats occurs an array of conservative species, many of them with affinities to the Coastal Plain. Such flats occur here and there throughout our southern and eastern sectors, off the moraines in the Lake Plain and in the Kankakee Sand Sections. Each such area has its own distinctive flora; characteristic conservative species in the aggregate include &lt;em&gt;Aletris farinosa&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Buchnera americana&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Calopogon tuberosus&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Carex alata&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Carex atlantica&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Cyperus dentatus&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Eleocharis melanocarpa&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Eleocharis microcarpa filiculmis&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Hypericum adpressum&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Hypericum canadense&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Hypericum gymnanthum&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Juncus biflorus&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Juncus nodatus&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Linum intercursum&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Linum striatum&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Ludwigia sphaerocarpa deamii&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Lycopodium inundatum&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Lycopus amplectens&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Panicum polyanthes&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Panicum verrucosum&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Polygala cruciata aquilonia&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Psilocarya scirpoides&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Rhynchospora globularis recognita&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Rhynchospora macrostachya&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Rubus setosus&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Salix lucida&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Scirpus hallii&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Scleria pauciflora caroliniana&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Utricularia subulata&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Viola primulifolia&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Xyris difformis&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;Xyris torta&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;ruderal-areas&#34;&gt;Ruderal Areas&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is presumed that many of our non-conservative native species developed their &amp;ldquo;weedy&amp;rdquo; tendencies in connection with the Native American peoples, particular those who were sedentary and agricultural.  These plants are well adapted to soils regularly disturbed mechanically, subject to heavy trampling or compaction, or to very fertile soils free of conservative competition. In the drier soils such species include &lt;em&gt;Acalypha rhomboidea&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Agrostis hyemalis&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Amaranthus hybridus&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Ambrosia artemisiifolia elatior&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Aristida aligantha&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Asclepias syriaca&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Asclepias verticillata&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Aster pilosus&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Bidens vulgata&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Brassica kaber&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Carex blanda&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Cenchrus longispinus&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Convolvulus sepium&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Cuscuta campestris&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Equisetum arvense&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Eragrostis pectinacea&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Erigeron annuus&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Erigeron canadensis&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Euphorbia maculata&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Euphorbia supina&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Galium aparine&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Geum canadense&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Juncus tenuis&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Lepidium virginicum&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Muhlenbergia schreberi&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Oenothera biennis&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Oxalis europaea&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Oxalis stricta&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Panicum capillare&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Physalis subglabrata&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Phytolacca americana&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Plantago aristata&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Plantago rugelii&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Plantago virginica&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Polygonum achoreum&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Polygonum buxiforme&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Polygonum scandens&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Potentilla norvegica&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Rhus glabra&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Rhus typhina&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Rudbeckia hirta&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Silene antirrhina&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Solanum americanum&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Solidago altissima&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Solidago canadensis&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Sporobolus vaginiflorus&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Verbena bracteata&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;Veronica peregrina&lt;/em&gt;. Plants of moister or wetter ruderal ground include &lt;em&gt;Acer negundo&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Acer saccharmum Acnida altissima&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Alopecurus carolinianus&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Ambrosia trifida&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Bidens frondosa&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Cornus racemosa&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Cyperus esculentus&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Cyperus strigosus&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Echinochloa crusgalli&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Panicum dichotomiflorum&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Polygonum lapathifolium&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Polygonum pensylvanicum&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Ranunculus abortivus&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Rumex maritimus fueginus&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Salix interior&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Sambucus canadensis&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Typha angustifolia&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;Typha latifolia&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;boreal-and-coastal-plain-relicts&#34;&gt;Boreal and Coastal Plain Relicts&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An interesting aspect of the Chicago region is its position at the southern end of Lake Michigan with its Lake Plain flora, coupled with the large sand district associated with the Kankakee River.  Together these singular areas have provided a remarkable context for habitats that support species otherwise more common northward or with their principal range in the Atlantic Coastal Plain. Many of these plants and their habitats, especially those which occur in the Indiana dune region, are discussed at length by Wilhelm.&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:12&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:12&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;12&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Those plants with an affinity for the Coastal Plain include &lt;em&gt;Ammophila breviligulata&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Aristida tuberculosa&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Bartonia virginica&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Bidens discoidea&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Cakile edentula&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Carex alata&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Carex albolutescens&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Carex debilis&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Carex longii&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Carex seorsa&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Cirsium pitcheri&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Cladium mariscoides&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Decodon verticillatus&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Drosera intermedia&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Drosera rotundifolia&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Eleocharis olivacea&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Eleocharis equisetoides&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Eleocharis geniculata&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Eleocharis melanocarpa&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Eleocharis microcarpa filiculmis&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Eleocharis robbinsii&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Eriocaulon septangulare&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Euphorbia polygonifolia&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Fimbristylis drummondii&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Fuirena pumila&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Gratiola aurea&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Hudsonia tomentosa&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Hydrocotyle umbellata&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Hypericum virginicum&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Juncus balticus littoralis&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Juncus militaris&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Juncus pelocarpus&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Juncus scirpoides&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Lathyrus japonicus glaber&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Lechea pulchella&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Linum striatum&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Ludwigia sphaerocarpadeamii&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Lycopodium inundatum&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Panicum lucidum&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Panicumoligosanthes&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Panicum spretum&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Panicum verrucosum&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Peltandra virginica&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Polygala cruciata aquilonia&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Polygonella articulata&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Polygonum careyi&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Polygonum opelousanum adenocalyx&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Potamogeton pulcher&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Psilocarya nitens&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Psilocarya scirpoides&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Rhexia virginica&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Rhynchospora alba&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Rhynchospora globularis recognita&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Rhynchospora macrostachya&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Scirpus purshianus&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Scleria reticularis&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Sisyrinchium atlanticum&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Solidago tenuifolia&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Stachys hyssopifolia&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Utricularia cornuta&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Utricularia geminiscapa&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Utricularia gibba&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Utricularia inflata minor&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Utricularia purpurea&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Utricularia resupinata&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Utricularia subulata&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Viola primulifolia&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Woodwardia virginica&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Xyris difformis&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;Xyris torta&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Plants believed to be relicts of a more boreal flora include &lt;em&gt;Andromeda glaucophylla&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Arctostaphylos uva-ursi coactilis&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Betula alleghaniensis&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Betula papyrifera&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Betula populifolia&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Betula pumila&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Calla palustris&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Campanula rotundifolia&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Carex eburnea&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Chamaedaphne calyculata angustifolia&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Circaea alpina&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Comptonia peregrina&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Coptis groenlandica&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Cornus rugosa&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Cypripedium reginae&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Diervilla lonicera&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Epigaea repens&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Glyceria borealis&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Habenaria clavellata&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Habenaria hyperborea huronensis&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Juniperus communis&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Linnaea borealis americana&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Maianthemum canadense&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Myosotis laxa&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Panax trifolius&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Pinus banksiana&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Pinus strobus&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Poa paludigena&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Polygala paucifolia&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Potentilla fruticosa&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Pyrola elliptica&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Pyrola rotundifolia americana&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Rhamnus alnifolia&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Salix candida&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Salix syrticola&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Spiranthes lucida&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Thuja occidentalis&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Trientalis borealis&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Vaccinium macrocarpon&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;Vaccinium oxycoccos&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnotes&#34;&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:1&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Homoya M.A., Abrell, D.B., Aldrich, J.R., Post, T.W. (1985). &lt;a href=&#34;https://journals.indianapolis.iu.edu/index.php/ias/article/view/8352&#34;&gt;The Natural Regions of Indiana&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;i&gt;Proc. Ind. Acad. Sci.&lt;/i&gt; 94, 245-268&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref1:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref2:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:2&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Schwegman, J.E. (1973). &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;https://naturalheritage.illinois.gov/content/dam/soi/en/web/naturalheritage/documents/Natural%20divisions%20part%202.pdf&#34;&gt;Comprehensive plan for the Illinois nature preserve system. Part 2: the natural divisions of Illinois&lt;/a&gt;.&amp;rdquo; Rockford, Ill.: Published by the Illinois Nature Preserves Commission.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref1:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref2:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:3&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Albert, D.A., Denton, S.R., Barnes, B.V. (1986). &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.2737/NC-GTR-178&#34;&gt;Regional landscape ecosystems of Michigan&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;University of Michigan, School of Natural Resources&lt;/em&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref1:3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:4&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Albert (in press)&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:4&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:5&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hole &amp;amp; Germain (in press)&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:5&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:6&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ellsworth, H.L. (1837). &lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://lccn.loc.gov/16000813&#34;&gt;Illinois in 1837&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/i&gt;. Philadelphia: Published by S. Augustus Mitchell, and by Grigg and Elliot.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:6&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref1:6&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref2:6&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:7&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Brown, S.R. (1817) &lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://archive.org/details/westerngazetteer00inbrow&#34;&gt;The western gazetteer; or emigrant&amp;rsquo;s directory, containing a geographical description of the western states and territories&amp;hellip;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/i&gt; Auburn, N.Y.: Published by H.C. Southwick.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:7&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref1:7&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:8&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Parker, A.A. (1835) &lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://lccn.loc.gov/01008713&#34;&gt;Trip to the West and Texas&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/i&gt;. Concord, Mass.: Published by White and Fisher.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:8&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref1:8&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref2:8&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref3:8&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:9&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pratt, H.E. (1835) &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.jstor.org/stable/40189796&#34;&gt;John Dean Caton&amp;rsquo;s reminiscences of Chicago in 1833 and 1834&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;i&gt;J. Ill. State Hist. Soc.&lt;/i&gt; 28(1), 5-25&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:9&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:10&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Coffinberry, S.C. (1880) Incidents connected with the first settlement of Nottawa-Sippi Prairie in St. Joseph County. &lt;em&gt;Mich. Pioneer Hist. Coll.&lt;/em&gt; 2:489-501&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:10&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:11&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Eleven percent of our native species have &lt;em&gt;C&lt;/em&gt; values from 0-3, 89% from 4-10.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:11&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:12&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wilhelm, G.S. (1990) &lt;a href=&#34;https://pubs.nps.gov/eTIC/HOSP-INDU/INDU_626_D92_0376pg.pdf&#34;&gt;Special vegetation of the Indiana Dunes National Lakeshore&lt;/a&gt;. Indiana Dunes National Lakeshore Research Program, Report 90-02. Published by the National Park Service.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:12&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
	</item>
	
	</channel>
</rss>
